<chapter number="10" id="corty3e-ch10-chapter-10" title="10 Between-Subjects, One-Way Analysis of Variance" start-numbering-at="10" numbered="true">
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="329">
<p id="corty3e_page_329" block_type="page_start">329</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p1" block_type="chapter_number">10</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p2" block_type="chapter_title">Between-Subjects, One-Way Analysis of Variance</p>
<box numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-ibx-1" block_type="intro_box">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p3" block_type="obj-h"><strong>LEARNING OBJECTIVES</strong></p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="bluesquare">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p4" block_type="obj-bl">Explain when ANOVA is used and how it works.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p5" block_type="obj-bl">Complete a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p6" block_type="obj-bl">Interpret the results of a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p7" block_type="obj-h"><strong>CHAPTER OVERVIEW</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p11" block_type="co-txt-ni"><link href="corty3e-ch08.xml">Chapters 8</link> and <link href="corty3e-ch09.xml">9</link> covered two-sample <em>t</em> tests, tests that compare the means of two groups to see if they have a statistically significant difference. <em>t</em> tests are great for experiments with just two groups, like classic experiments with a control group and an experimental group. A <em>t</em> test would work well, for example, to see if a medication works better than a placebo in treating an illness. However, experiments that address complex questions often require more than two groups. Finding the best way to treat an illness might involve comparing three different medications and three different doses of each medication, ending up with nine different groups. The statistical technique that compares means when there are more than two groups is called analysis of variance.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p8" block_type="co-toc-h1-t"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-sec1-1"><phrase block_type="co-toc-h1-n-ri">10.1</phrase> Introduction to Analysis of Variance</link></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p9" block_type="co-toc-h1-t"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-sec1-2"><phrase block_type="co-toc-h1-n-ri">10.2</phrase> Calculating Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</link></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p10" block_type="co-toc-h1-t"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-sec1-3"><phrase block_type="co-toc-h1-n-ri">10.3</phrase> Interpreting Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</link></p>
</box>
</box>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec1-1" block_type="h1" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="329">
<section-metadata><section-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">10.1</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Introduction to Analysis of Variance</phrase></section-title></section-metadata>
<box id="corty3e-ch10-video-1" block_type="video">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-videotxt-1" block_type="vidtxt"><link href="http://bcs.whfreeman.com/webpub/statistics/ips7e/student/Stat Videos/ch12/sc_anova_bi.html" target="_pop" data-href-px=""><image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-vimg-1" alt="image" src="asset/images/video.jpg"/></link><em>StatClips: ANOVA – Background and Introduction</em>Video on LaunchPad</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec2-1" block_type="h2" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="329">
<section-metadata><section-title>Analysis of Variance Terminology</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p12" block_type="txt-ni"><termref term="analysis of variance (ANOVA)">Analysis of variance</termref>, called <termref term="analysis of variance (ANOVA)">ANOVA</termref> for short, is a family of statistical tests used for comparing the means of two or more groups. This chapter focuses on <termref term="between-subjects one-way ANOVA">between-subjects, one-way ANOVA</termref>. Between-subjects, one-way ANOVA is an extension of the independent-samples <em>t</em> test, so it is used to compare means when there are two or more <em>independent</em> samples.</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-2" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p13" block_type="bl-first"><strong>Between-subjects</strong> is ANOVA terminology for independent samples.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p14" block_type="bl-mid"><termref term="way">Way</termref> is ANOVA terminology for an explanatory variable. Ways can either be independent variables or grouping variables. (Independent variables are controlled by the experimenter, who assigns subjects to groups. Grouping variables are naturally occurring characteristics used to classify subjects into different groups.)</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_330" block_type="page_start">330</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p15" block_type="bl-mid">A one-way ANOVA has one explanatory variable, either an independent variable or a grouping variable. A two-way ANOVA would have two explanatory variables, a three-way ANOVA would have three, etc.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p16" block_type="bl-mid">Though the explanatory variable in ANOVA is either a grouping variable or an independent variable, it becomes tedious to use both terms. Most statisticians get a bit casual with language and simply call it an independent variable; we&#8217;ll continue calling them, generically, explanatory variables. Of course, when it is an independent variable, we&#8217;ll call it that.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p17" block_type="bl-mid">An explanatory variable in ANOVA is also called a <termref term="factor">factor</termref><strong>,</strong> so a one-way ANOVA can also be called a one-factor ANOVA.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p18" block_type="bl-last"><termref term="level">Level</termref> is the term in ANOVA for a category of an explanatory variable. The grouping variable sex, for example, has two levels&#8212;male and female.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p19" block_type="txt">To clarify all this terminology, here&#8217;s a question where a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA would be used: Is there a difference in artistic ability among right-handed, left-handed, and ambidextrous people? This question could be answered by gathering a sample of people and classifying them into three groups: (1) right-handed people, (2) left-handed people, and (3) ambidextrous people.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p20" block_type="txt">Now there are three samples. The samples are independent samples as who is in one sample does not control or determine who is in another sample.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p21" block_type="txt">Next, artistic ability is measured with an interval-level scale. Because the dependent variable, artistic ability, is measured at the interval level, the mean level for each of the three groups can be calculated. Means can also be calculated for ratio-level variables, so ANOVA may be used when the outcome variable is measured at the interval or ratio level.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p22" block_type="txt"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-1"><strong>Table 10.1</strong></link> illustrates this experiment with one cell for each sample. There is one row with three columns. The row represents the explanatory variable of handedness, what in ANOVA terminology is called the <em>way</em> or the <em>factor.</em> The columns represent the three <em>levels</em> of the explanatory variable: right-handed, left-handed, and ambidextrous.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-1" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-1" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_01.jpg"/>
</figure>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec2-2" block_type="h2" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="330">
<section-metadata><section-title>Why ANOVA Is Needed</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p23" block_type="txt-ni"><em>t</em> tests compare means between groups, so why is analysis of variance even needed? ANOVA is needed in order to keep the risk of Type I error at a reasonable level when comparing means of multiple groups. (Remember: Type I error occurs when a researcher erroneously concludes that there is a statistically significant difference.)</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p24" block_type="txt">To see why this is a problem, consider a study with five conditions&#8212;for example, four different medications and a placebo being tested in treating some disease. It would be possible to analyze the data from these five conditions using a series of <em>t</em> tests. For example, a researcher could compare the mean of Condition 1 to Condition 2, the mean of Condition 1 to Condition 3, the mean of Condition 1 to Condition 4, and so on as shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-2"><strong>Table 10.2</strong></link>. This would require completing 10 <em>t</em> tests.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_331" block_type="page_start">331</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-2" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-2" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_02.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p25" block_type="txt">It is tedious to do 10 <em>t</em> tests, but that is not why ANOVA is preferred. The real problem is that the likelihood of making a Type I error increases as the number of <em>t</em> tests increases. Scientists usually set alpha, the probability of a Type I error, at .05, so that they have a 5&#37; chance of making this error. But, with 10 separate tests, the <em>overall</em> alpha level rises to be close to 50&#37;. This means that there is close to a 50&#37; chance that 1 of the 10 <em>t</em> tests will reach the wrong conclusion, rejecting the null hypothesis when it is true. Those are not good odds. And, the experimenter won&#8217;t know which, if any, of the statistically significant results is erroneous.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p26" block_type="txt">Analysis of variance solves the problem of having a large risk of Type I error, what statisticians call runaway alpha. With ANOVA, one test is completed with a specified chance of Type I error. As with <em>t</em> tests, the alpha level, the chance of committing a Type I error, is usually set at .05. One test&#8212;the ANOVA&#8212;compares all the means at once and determines if any two of the means have a statistically significant difference. If the ANOVA is statistically significant, then the researcher performs what is called a post-hoc test. A <termref term="post-hoc test">post-hoc test</termref> is a follow-up test, engineered to find out which pairs of means differ while keeping the overall alpha level at a specified level, again, usually .05.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p27" block_type="txt">Here&#8217;s a metaphor for how analysis of variance and post-hoc tests work together. Imagine standing outside of a football stadium on the day of a big game and hearing a loud roar. From the roar, one would know that something significant has happened in the game. That&#8217;s analysis of variance&#8212;it indicates, in general, that something interesting has happened, but it doesn&#8217;t state specifically what happened. To find out what has happened at the game, one needs to buy a ticket and go into the stadium. Going into the stadium is like doing a post-hoc test. Post-hoc tests are only conducted in analysis of variance when one is sure there is something interesting to be found.</p>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec2-3" block_type="h2" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="331">
<section-metadata><section-title>What ANOVA Does</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p28" block_type="txt-ni">With this background on ANOVA, let&#8217;s learn why it is called analysis of variance and how it works. ANOVA works by analyzing a set of scores and separating out the different sources of variability in the scores.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p29" block_type="txt">To understand this, imagine investigating the effect of alcohol on intoxication. Suppose research participants come to a laboratory where each person consumes one beer. After 20 minutes, researchers measure the level of intoxication by observing the effects of the alcohol on each person&#8217;s performance on a behavioral task, say, walking a straight line. The higher the intoxication score, the poorer is the ability to walk in a straight line.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_332" block_type="page_start">332</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p30" block_type="txt"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-3"><strong>Figure 10.1</strong></link> shows the expected results&#8212;not everyone would have exactly the same intoxication score. Rather, there is variability in the scores&#8212;with some people acting quite intoxicated, some people not acting at all intoxicated, and most clustered around the average score. Even though everyone received <em>exactly</em> the same dose of alcohol, not everyone reacted in <em>exactly</em> the same way. This variability <em>within</em> a group that receives the same treatment is called <termref term="within-group variability">within-group variability</termref><strong>.</strong> Within-group variability is primarily caused by individual differences, attributes that vary from case to case. So, how much one weighs, how recently one has eaten, and how much prior experience one has had with alcohol will all affect a person&#8217;s intoxication score. These are all individual difference factors.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-3" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-3" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_01.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.1</phrase> Distribution of Intoxication Scores for Participants Who Consumed One Beer</strong> Even though all participants received exactly the same dose of alcohol, there was variability in how it affected them. Some people exhibited very little intoxication and other people showed more. This variability within the group is accounted for by individual differences such as sex, weight, time since last meal, and prior experience with alcohol.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p31" block_type="txt">Within-group variability can be reduced by making the sample more homogeneous, but the effect of individual differences can&#8217;t be eliminated entirely. For example, if all participants were men who weighed 175 pounds, had eaten dinner 30 minutes ago, and had been consuming alcohol regularly for over a year, there would still be variability within that group on the intoxication scores.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p32" block_type="txt">Within-group variability is one type of variability in analysis of variance. The other type of variability for a one-way ANOVA is <em>between-group variability.</em> <termref term="Between-group variability">Between-group variability</termref> is variability that is due to the different &#8220;treatments&#8221; that the different groups receive.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p33" block_type="txt"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-4"><strong>Figure 10.2</strong></link> shows the distribution of intoxication scores for two groups&#8212;one group where each participant drank one beer and one group where each participant drank a six-pack. Individual differences explain the variability within a group, but the different doses of alcohol explain the differences <em>between</em> groups, why one group is more intoxicated than the other. This is called the <termref term="treatment effect">treatment effect</termref> because it refers to the different ways that groups are treated. The treatment effect shows up as an impact on the outcome variable (here, the intoxication score) and is associated with the explanatory variable (here, the dose of alcohol, which is controlled by the experimenter).</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_333" block_type="page_start">333</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-4" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-4" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_02.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.2</phrase> Distributions of Intoxication Scores for Participants Who Consumed Different Amounts of Alcohol</strong> The curve on the left is the distribution of intoxication scores for participants who consumed one beer. The curve on the right is the distribution of scores for participants who consumed six beers. Note that within each group there is variability in the intoxication level, variability due to individual differences. There is also variability <em>between</em> the two groups. The easiest way to see this is to observe that the two curves have different midpoints, with one group having a higher average score than the other.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p34" block_type="txt">Between-group variability in one-way ANOVA is made up of two things: the treatment effect and individual differences. We&#8217;ve already covered how treatment plays a role in between-group variability. Now, let&#8217;s see how individual differences play a role in between-group variability.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p35" block_type="txt">Imagine a large group of people randomly divided into two groups. Because of random assignment, the two groups should be fairly similar in terms of sex, weight, time since last meal, experience with alcohol, and so on. Now, each person in each group consumes the same dose of alcohol and is measured for intoxication level. Both groups are similar in terms of their characteristics and receive exactly the same treatment. Will the mean intoxication scores of the two groups be exactly the same? No. Because individual differences exist, the two groups will have slightly different means. Between-group variability is due <em>both</em> to individual differences and treatment effect.</p>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec2-4" block_type="h2" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="333">
<section-metadata><section-title>How ANOVA Uses Variability</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p36" block_type="txt-ni">To understand how ANOVA uses within-group variability and between-group variability to see if there is a statistically significant difference, look at the two panels in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-5"><strong>Figure 10.3</strong></link>. Each panel represents groups that are randomly assigned to receive three different treatments for some illness. Treatment, the explanatory variable, has three levels. The top panel (A) depicts an outcome where there is little impact of treatment on outcome.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-5" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.3" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-5" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_03a_b.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.3</phrase> Examples of Little Impact of Treatment on Outcome and a Lot of Impact of Treatment on Outcome</strong> In the top panel (A), the three different treatments have about the same average effect on outcome. Note that the three means (<em>M</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>M</em><sub>3</sub>) are very close to each other and that there is a lot of overlap in outcome from group to group. In contrast, the bottom panel (B) shows three treatments with very different effects on outcome. In it, the three means (<em>M</em><sub>4</sub> to <em>M</em><sub>6</sub>) are further apart from each other and there is no overlap in outcome from group to group.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p37" block_type="txt">The top panel shows little effect of the independent variable because the three means (<em>M</em><sub>1</sub>, <em>M</em><sub>2</sub>, and <em>M</em><sub>3</sub>) are very close to each other. In contrast, the bottom panel (B), where the means (<em>M</em><sub>4</sub>, <em>M</em><sub>5</sub>, and <em>M</em><sub>6</sub>) are far apart, shows that treatment has an impact on outcome because the different treatments lead to dramatically different outcomes.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_334" block_type="page_start">334</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p38" block_type="txt">Analysis of variance could be used to analyze these results. ANOVA would show that the results in the top panel are not statistically significant, while the results in the bottom panel are statistically significant. How does analysis of variance lead to these conclusions?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p39" block_type="txt">Look at the means in each panel. Note that there is little variability among the means in the top panel and a lot of variability among the means in the bottom panel. Little variability exists in the top panel as all the means are close to each other. The greater distance between the means in the bottom panel indicates more variability between the means there. In the language of ANOVA, there is more <em>between-group variability</em> when the effect of treatment is large (the bottom panel) than when the effect of treatment is small (the top panel).</p>
<box numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p40" block_type="mn-ext-ni"><em>One-way analysis of variance calculates the ratio of between-group variability to within-group variability.</em></p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p41" block_type="txt"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-6"><strong>Figure 10.4</strong></link> shows how the total variability in the data is partitioned into between-group variability and within-group variability. To decide if the amount of between-group variability is large or small, ANOVA compares it to within-group variability. One-way analysis of variance calculates the ratio of between-group variability to within-group variability. This is called an <em>F</em> ratio, in honor of Sir Ronald Fisher, who developed the procedure.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-6" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.4" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-6" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_04.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.4</phrase> Partitioning Variability into Between-Group and Within-Group Variability</strong> The panel on the left shows little effect of treatment on outcome as only a small piece of the total variability is explained by differences between groups. In contrast, in the panel on the right, where a large piece of the total variability is accounted for by differences between groups, there is a large effect of treatment on outcome.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-1" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-7" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_334_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p42" block_type="txt">The <em>F</em> ratio works because within-group variability is made up of individual differences, while between-group variability includes treatment effect <em>and</em> individual differences. So, the <em>F</em> ratio could be rewritten as</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-2" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-8" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_334_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e_page_335" block_type="page_start">335</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p43" block_type="txt">Here&#8217;s what the <em>F</em> ratio, also known just as <em>F,</em> means:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-3" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p44" block_type="bl-first">If there is no treatment effect, then there is no variability due to treatment and the variability indicated by the numerator of the <em>F</em> ratio is due only to individual differences.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p45" block_type="bl-mid">As a result, the <em>F</em> ratio has the same numerator (individual differences variability) and denominator (individual differences variability), so it will equal 1.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p46" block_type="bl-mid">As the effect of treatment grows, the numerator becomes larger than the denominator, and the <em>F</em> ratio climbs above 1. (Remember, treatment effect refers to the impact of the explanatory variable.)</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p47" block_type="bl-mid">As the <em>F</em> ratio increases, as it climbs higher above 1, the results are more likely to be statistically significant.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p48" block_type="bl-last">As variability is never negative, the <em>F</em> ratio can&#8217;t go below 0.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p49" block_type="txt"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-9"><strong>Figure 10.5</strong></link> gives an example of what the <em>F</em> distribution looks like. Note that it starts at 0, has a mode near 1, and tails off to the right. <em>F</em> gets bigger when there is more between-group variability than within-group variability.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_336" block_type="page_start">336</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-9" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.5" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-9" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_05.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.5</phrase> An Example of a Sampling Distribution for the <em>F</em> Ratio</strong> This is an example of a sampling distribution for the <em>F</em> ratio, the ratio of between-group variability to within-group variability. Note that <em>F</em> can&#8217;t be lower than zero, that the high point of the curve is close to a value of 1 on the <em>X</em>-axis, that the distribution is positively skewed, and that the probability decreases as <em>F</em> gets larger than 1.</caption>
</figure>
<box title="A Common Question" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx1-1" block_type="bx-1-h">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p50" block_type="bx1-que"><strong>Q</strong> Looking at the ratio of between-group variability to within-group variability is a clever way to see if means differ. Could an ANOVA be used instead of a <em>t</em> test when there are just two groups?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p51" block_type="bx1-ans"><strong>A</strong> Yes. ANOVA can be used when comparing <em>two</em> or more means. In fact, a <em>t</em> test is just a variation on ANOVA. If a researcher has two groups, calculates a <em>t</em> value, and then squares the <em>t</em> value, it will be equal to the <em>F</em> ratio obtained by analyzing the same data with an ANOVA.</p>
</box>
<box title="Practice Problems 10.1" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx2-1" block_type="sr-h">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p52" block_type="sr-h1"><strong>Review Your Knowledge</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p53" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.1</phrase> What makes up within-group variability?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p54" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.2</phrase> What makes up between-group variability?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p55" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.3</phrase> An <em>F</em> ratio is a ratio of what divided by what?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p56" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.4</phrase> When is a post-hoc test used?</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec1-2" block_type="h1" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="336">
<section-metadata><section-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">10.2</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Calculating Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></section-title></section-metadata>
<box id="corty3e-ch10-video-2" block_type="video">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-videotxt-2" block_type="vidtxt"><link href="http://bcs.whfreeman.com/webpub/statistics/ips7e/student/Stat Videos/ch12/sc_anova_inference.html" target="_pop" data-href-px=""><image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-vimg-2" alt="image" src="asset/images/video.jpg"/></link><em>StatClips: ANOVA - Inference</em>Video on LaunchPad</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p57" block_type="txt-ni">Imagine that Dr. Chung, a psychologist who studies learning and motivation, designed a study to learn whether rats could discriminate among different types of food and if this discrimination influenced their behavior. He built a large and complex maze and trained 10 rats to run it. A rat would be placed in the start box and had to find its way to the goal box. To motivate the rats, food was placed in the goal box. Dr. Chung trained the rats with three different types of food: a low-calorie food, a normal-calorie food, and a high-calorie food. Each rat received an equal number of trials with each food and the rats were trained until they all ran the maze equally quickly.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_337" block_type="page_start">337</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-10" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="small" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-10" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_un01.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p58" block_type="txt">Dr. Chung then put all the rats on a diet until they lost 10&#37; of their normal body weight. The purpose of this was to increase their motivation to find food. Up until this point, all the rats had received the same treatment. Now, Dr. Chung implemented his experimental manipulation.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p59" block_type="txt">He randomly assigned the rats to three groups based on the type of food they would find in the goal box the next time they ran the maze: low-calorie, medium-calorie, or high-calorie. Each rat, individually, was placed in the maze and allowed to approach the goal box. When the rat got there, however, it found a screen that prevented it from entering. The rat could see and smell the food through the screen, but it couldn&#8217;t get to the food. The purpose of this was to inform the rat of the type of food that awaited it.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p60" block_type="txt">Dr. Chung picked up the rat, removed the screen, and placed the rat in the start box. He then timed, in seconds, how long it took the rat to get to the goal box. This is the dependent variable in his study and the fewer seconds it took the rat to get to the goal box, the faster the rat traveled the maze. Dr. Chung figured that if the different caloric contents of the foods had been recognized by the rats and if hungry rats were more motivated by higher-calorie foods, then the time taken to run the maze should differ among the three groups. The data and the means for the three groups are shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-11"><strong>Table 10.3</strong></link>.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-11" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.3" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-11" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_03.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p61" block_type="txt">The average was 31.00 seconds to get to the low-calorie food, 28.00 seconds for the medium-calorie food, and 25.00 seconds for the high-calorie food (<link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-12"><strong>Figure 10.6</strong></link>). It appears as if mean speed increases as calorie content goes up, but the effect is not dramatic. It seems possible that the differences among the three groups may be explained by sampling error. It is also possible that the calorie content of the food in the goal box has had an effect. A statistical test is needed to decide between these two options.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-12" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.6" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-12" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_06.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.6</phrase> The Effect of Calorie Content on Maze Travel Time</strong> There appears to be some decrease in the mean time it takes a rat to run the maze (i.e., an increase in speed) as the calorie content of the food in the goal box increases. But, the effect looks modest at best. A between-subjects, one-way ANOVA can be used to see if the effect is a statistically significant one or if the differences are due to sampling error.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_338" block_type="page_start">338</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p62" block_type="h4"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 1</strong></phrase> <strong>Pick a Test</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p63" block_type="txt-ni">The first step of hypothesis testing is picking the right test. This study compares the means of three independent samples. There is one independent variable (calorie content), which has three levels (low, medium, and high). The dependent variable, seconds, is measured at the ratio level, so means can be calculated. This study calls for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-13" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-13" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_un02.jpg"/>
<caption>Don&#8217;t forget: <strong>T</strong>om <strong>a</strong>nd <strong>H</strong>arry <strong>d</strong>espise <strong>c</strong>rabby <strong>i</strong>nfants is a mnemonic to remember the six steps of hypothesis testing.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_339" block_type="page_start">339</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p64" block_type="h4"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 2</strong></phrase> <strong>Check the Assumptions</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p65" block_type="txt-ni">The assumptions for the between-subjects, one-way ANOVA, listed in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-14"><strong>Table 10.4</strong></link>, are the same as they are for an independent-samples <em>t</em> test: (1) each sample should be a random sample from its population, (2) the cases should be independent of each other, (3) the dependent variable should be normally distributed in each population, and (4) each population should have the same degree of variability. The robustness of the assumptions is the same as for <em>t.</em> The only nonrobust assumption is the second one, the assumption of independence of observations within each group.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-14" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.4" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-14" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_04.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p66" block_type="txt">Here is an evaluation of the assumptions for the maze data:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-4" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p67" block_type="nl-first"><em>Random samples.</em> Though this is an experimental study in which cases were randomly assigned to experimental conditions, the initial sample wasn&#8217;t a random sample from the population of rats, so this assumption was violated. The assumption is robust, however, so Dr. Chung can proceed. However, he has to be careful about generalizing beyond the specific strain of rats he&#8217;s working with.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p68" block_type="nl-mid"><em>Independence of cases.</em> Each rat was trained and tested individually. Each rat only provided one data point for the final test. So, this assumption was not violated.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p69" block_type="nl-mid"><em>Normality.</em> It seems reasonable to assume that, within a population of rats, running speed is normally distributed. That is, for rats, there is a mean speed around which most animals cluster and the number of rats with higher and lower speeds tails off in both directions symmetrically.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p70" block_type="nl-last"><em>Homogeneity of variance.</em> A look at the three standard deviations (1.00, 0.82, and 1.00) shows that they are all about the same. There is no reason to believe that this assumption has been violated.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p71" block_type="txt-ni">With no nonrobust assumptions violated, Dr. Chung can proceed with the planned between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p72" block_type="h4"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 3</strong></phrase> <strong>List the Hypotheses</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p73" block_type="txt-ni">The hypotheses are statements about the populations. In Dr. Chung&#8217;s study, there are three samples, with each one thought of as having come from a separate population. His hypotheses will be about the population of rats that finds low-calorie food in the goal box, the population of rats that finds medium-calorie food, and the population of rats that finds high-calorie food.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_340" block_type="page_start">340</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p74" block_type="txt">Look at <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-9">Figure 10.5</link>, the example of a sampling distribution for an <em>F</em> ratio, and notice two things&#8212;there are no negative values on the <em>x</em>-axis and the sampling distribution is positively skewed. It looks like there is only one &#8220;tail&#8221; to the sampling distribution. This doesn&#8217;t mean that all ANOVAs are one-tailed; it means just the opposite. Both &#8220;tails&#8221; are wrapped into this one side, so ANOVA always has nondirectional hypotheses. One doesn&#8217;t have to decide between a one-tailed or two-tailed test. ANOVA is always two-tailed.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p75" block_type="txt">The nondirectional null hypothesis will state that no difference exists in the means of the populations. The generic form of this, where there are <em>k</em> samples, is</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p76" block_type="eq"><em>H</em><sub>0</sub>: &#956;<sub>1</sub> &#61; &#956;<sub>2</sub> &#61; . . . &#61; &#956;<sub>k</sub></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p77" block_type="txt-ni">For the maze study, with three populations, Dr. Chung&#8217;s null hypothesis is</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p78" block_type="eq"><em>H</em><sub>0</sub>: &#956;<sub>1</sub> &#61; &#956;<sub>2</sub> &#61; &#956;<sub>3</sub></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p79" block_type="txt">The alternative hypothesis, also nondirectional, says not all population means are equal. It is not written as &#956;<sub>1</sub> &#8800; &#956;<sub>2</sub> &#8800; &#956;<sub>3</sub> because that doesn&#8217;t cover options like Populations 1 and 2 having different means but Populations 2 and 3 don&#8217;t. The alternative hypothesis states that at least two of the population means are different, and maybe all three are. There is no easy way to write this mathematically, so Dr. Chung will write it as</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p80" block_type="eq"><em>H</em><sub>1</sub>: At least one population mean is different from the others.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p81" block_type="h4"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 4</strong></phrase> <strong>Set the Decision Rule</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p82" block_type="txt-ni">This step finds the critical value of <em>F,</em> abbreviated <em>F<sub>cv</sub>,</em> the value that separates the rare zone from the common zone of the sampling distribution of the <em>F</em> ratio. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-15"><strong>Figure 10.7</strong></link> is an example of a sampling distribution of <em>F</em> with the rare and common zones marked.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-15" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.7" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-15" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_07.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.7</phrase> Using the Critical Value of <em>F</em> to Mark the Common Zone and the Rare Zone of the Sampling Distribution of <em>F</em></strong> The critical value of <em>F,</em> <em>F<sub>cv</sub>,</em> marks the boundary between the common zone and the rare zone of the test statistic. Here, 5&#37; of the area under the curve falls in the rare zone that is on and to the right of <em>F<sub>cv</sub>.</em></caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_341" block_type="page_start">341</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p83" block_type="txt">The decision rule will sound familiar as it is similar to what we used for the <em>z</em> test and <em>t</em> tests: if the calculated value of the test statistic, <em>F,</em> falls on the line or in the rare zone, the null hypothesis is rejected.</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-5" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p84" block_type="bl-first">If <em>F</em> &#8805; <em>F<sub>cv</sub>,</em> reject <em>H</em><sub>0</sub>.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p85" block_type="bl-last">If <em>F</em> &#60; <em>F<sub>cv</sub>,</em> fail to reject <em>H</em><sub>0</sub>.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p86" block_type="txt-ni">To obtain the value of <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em>, use <link href="corty3e_app1_1.html#corty3e-app1-fig-10">Appendix Table 4</link>. It provides two <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> tables: one for critical values of <em>F</em> with a 5&#37; chance of making a Type I error (i.e., &#945; &#61; .05) and one for a 1&#37; chance of making a Type I error (&#945; &#61; .01). A portion of the table with the most commonly used alpha level, .05, is shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-16"><strong>Table 10.5</strong></link>.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-16" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.5" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-16" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_05.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p87" block_type="txt">To determine the critical value of <em>F,</em> find the value at the intersection of the <em>column</em> for the degrees of freedom in the numerator and the <em>row</em> for the degrees of freedom in the denominator. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-1">Equation 10.1</link> shows how to calculate the different degrees of freedom needed for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA. Recall the formula for <em>F</em> ratio from the previous section:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-6" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p88" block_type="bl-first">The numerator degrees of freedom for the <em>F</em> ratio, what defines the columns in the table of critical values of <em>F,</em> are called between-groups degrees of freedom. This is abbreviated as <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub>.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p89" block_type="bl-mid">The denominator degrees of freedom for the <em>F</em> ratio, what defines the rows in the table of critical values of <em>F,</em> are within-groups degrees of freedom. This is abbreviated as <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p90" block_type="bl-last">The final degrees of freedom calculated in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-1">Equation 10.1</link> are total degrees of freedom. This is abbreviated as <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub> and represents the total number of degrees of freedom in the data. Note that adding together <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> equals <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub>.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e_page_342" block_type="page_start">342</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-1" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.1</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Degrees of Freedom for Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p91" block_type="eq"><em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; <em>k</em> &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p92" block_type="eq"><em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; <em>N</em> &#8211; <em>k</em></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p93" block_type="eq"><em>df</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; <em>N</em> &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p94" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; between-groups degrees of freedom (degrees of freedom for the numerator)</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p95" block_type="eq-unl"><em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; within-groups degrees of freedom (degrees of freedom for the denominator)</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p96" block_type="eq-unl"><em>df</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; total degrees of freedom</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p97" block_type="eq-unl"><em>k</em> &#61; the number of groups</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p98" block_type="eq-unl"><em>N</em> &#61; the total number of cases</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p99" block_type="txt">For the maze data, there are three groups (low-, medium-, and high-calorie), so <em>k</em> &#61; 3. There are a total of 10 participants in the study, so <em>N</em> &#61; 10. Given these values, degrees of freedom are calculated as</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p100" block_type="eq"><em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; <em>k</em> &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p101" block_type="eq">&#61; 3 &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p102" block_type="eq">&#61; 2</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p103" block_type="eq"><em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; <em>N</em> &#8211; <em>k</em></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p104" block_type="eq">&#61; 10 &#8211; 3</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p105" block_type="eq">&#61; 7</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p106" block_type="eq"><em>df</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; <em>N</em> &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p107" block_type="eq">&#61; 10 &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p108" block_type="eq">&#61; 9</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p109" block_type="txt">To find the critical value of <em>F,</em> Dr. Chung needs numerator degrees of freedom (<em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 2) and denominator degrees of freedom (<em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 7). The intersection of the column for 2 degrees of freedom and the row for 7 degrees of freedom leads to a critical value of <em>F</em> of 4.737. That means the decision rule for the maze data can now be written as:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-7" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p110" block_type="bl-first">If <em>F</em> &#8805; 4.737, reject the null hypothesis.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p111" block_type="bl-last">If <em>F</em> &#60; 4.737, fail to reject the null hypothesis.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p112" block_type="txt">The sampling distribution of <em>F</em> with degrees of freedom of 2 (numerator) and 7 (denominator) is shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-17"><strong>Figure 10.8</strong></link>. The critical value of <em>F,</em> <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> &#61; 4.737, is used to separate the rare zone from the common zone. If the observed value of <em>F,</em> the value of the test statistic calculated in Step 5, falls on the line or in the rare zone, the null hypothesis is rejected. If it falls in the common zone, Dr. Chung will fail to reject the null hypothesis.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-17" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.8" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-17" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_08.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.8</phrase> The Critical Value of <em>F</em> for 2 and 7 Degrees of Freedom</strong> The critical value of <em>F,</em> <em>F<sub>cv</sub>,</em> with 2 degrees of freedom in the numerator and 7 degrees of freedom in the denominator, is 4.737. Note that 5&#37; of the <em>F</em> distribution falls on or to the right of this point. If the observed value of <em>F</em> falls in the rare zone, then the null hypothesis is rejected.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_343" block_type="page_start">343</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p113" block_type="h4"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 5</strong></phrase> <strong>Calculate the Test Statistic</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p114" block_type="txt-ni">To complete the ANOVA, Dr. Chung&#8217;s next step is to analyze the variability in the maze data. This means taking account of variability both within and between groups:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-8" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p115" block_type="bl-first">Not each rat with the same type of food in the goal box coursed through the maze in the same amount of time, so there is variability within groups.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p116" block_type="bl-last">The three groups all had different means, so there is variability between groups.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p117" block_type="txt-ni">To understand why analysis of variance is called analysis of <em>variance,</em> it is useful to review the variance formula from <link href="corty3e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link>. Equation 3.6 says:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-3" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-18" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_343_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p118" block_type="txt">The <em>numerator</em> in the variance formula is calculated by following three steps: (1) calculating deviation scores by subtracting the mean from each score, (2) squaring all the deviation scores, and (3) adding up all the squared deviation scores. This numerator, a sum of squared deviation scores, is called a <em>sum of squares,</em> abbreviated as <em>SS.</em> Calculating sums of squares for the two sources of variability, between-groups and within-groups, is necessary to find the between- and within-group variances that are analyzed in an analysis of variance.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p119" block_type="txt">Actually, there are three sums of squares that are calculated. In addition to sum of squares between-groups (<em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>) and sum of squares within groups (<em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>), sum of squares total (<em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>) is also calculated. Sum of squares total represents all the variability in the data. Between-subjects, one-way ANOVA divides <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> into between-groups sum of squares (<em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>), which measures variability due to treatment, and within-groups sum of squares (<em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>), which measures variability due to individual differences. In other words, <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#43; <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_344" block_type="page_start">344</p>
<box numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-exp1-2" block_type="mn1">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p120" block_type="mn-ext-ni">SS<sub>Total</sub> <em>represents all the variability in the scores. Between-subjects, one-way ANOVA divides it into variability due to the different ways the groups are treated, and variability due to individual differences.</em></p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p121" block_type="txt"><termref term="sum of squares total">Sum of squares total</termref> is calculated by treating all the cases as if they belong in one group: the grand mean, the mean of all the scores, is subtracted from each score, these deviation scores are squared, and the squared deviation scores are added up. Voil&#224;, a sum of squares, the numerator for a variance.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p122" block_type="txt"><termref term="sum of squares between">Sum of squares between</termref> represents the variability between groups. It is calculated by subtracting the grand mean from each group mean, squaring these deviation scores, multiplying each squared deviation score by the number of cases in the group, and then adding them up. The final variance numerator, the one that represents variability within groups, <termref term="sum of squares within">sum of squares within</termref>, is calculated by taking each score, subtracting from it its group mean, squaring each deviation score, and adding them all up.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p123" block_type="txt">The calculations just described are what are called definitional formulas because the calculations explain what the value being calculated is. Unfortunately, definitional formulas often are not straightforward mathematically. In contrast, computational formulas are designed to be easier to use. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-2">Equation 10.2</link> is a computational formula for sum of squares total.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-2" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.2</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Formula for Calculating Sum of Squares Total for Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-4" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-19" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_344_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p124" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; total sum of squares</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p125" block_type="eq-unl"><em>X</em> &#61; raw score</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p126" block_type="eq-unl"><em>N</em> &#61; the total number of cases</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p127" block_type="txt-ni">This formula says:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p128" block_type="nl-first">Square each score and add them all up.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p129" block_type="nl-mid">Add up all the scores, square the sum, and divide by the total number of cases.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p130" block_type="nl-last">Subtract the result of Step 2 from the result of Step 1.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p131" block_type="txt">The easiest way to do this is to take <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-11">Table 10.3</link> and add another column to it, one for squared scores. This can be seen in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-20"><strong>Table 10.6</strong></link>. From the table, we can see that the sum of squared scores for Step 1 is 7,900.00.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-20" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.6" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-20" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_06.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_345" block_type="page_start">345</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p132" block_type="txt">Step 2 is next.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-5" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-21" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_345_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p133" block_type="txt">Finally,</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-6" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-22" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_345_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p134" block_type="txt-ni">Next, let&#8217;s use <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-3">Equation 10.3</link> to calculate sum of squares between groups.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-3" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.3</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Formula for Calculating Between-Groups Sum of Squares for Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-7" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-23" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_345_03.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p135" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; between-groups sum of squares</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p136" block_type="eq-unl"><em>X</em><sub>Group</sub> &#61; raw scores for cases in a group</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p137" block_type="eq-unl"><em>n</em><sub>Group</sub> &#61; number of cases in a group</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p138" block_type="eq-unl"><em>X</em> &#61; raw scores</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p139" block_type="eq-unl"><em>N</em> &#61; total number of cases</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p140" block_type="txt">Here&#8217;s how the formula works:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p141" block_type="nl-first">For each group, add up all the scores, square that sum, and divide that square by the number of cases in the group. Add up all these quotients.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p142" block_type="nl-mid">Add up all the scores, square that sum, and divide that square by the total number of cases.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p143" block_type="nl-last">Subtract Step 2 from Step 1.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p144" block_type="txt">Again, most of the work has already been done in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-20">Table 10.6</link>. Here is Step 1:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-8" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-24" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_345_04.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e_page_346" block_type="page_start">346</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p145" block_type="txt">And, Step 2:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-9" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-25" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_346_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p146" block_type="txt">Finally,</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-10" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-26" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_346_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p147" block_type="txt">The final sum of squares to calculate is the sum of squares within. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-4">Equation 10.4</link> covers this.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-4" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.4</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Formula for Calculating Sum of Squares Within for Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-11" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-27" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_346_03.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p148" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; sum of squares within</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p149" block_type="eq-unl"><em>X</em><sub>Group</sub> &#61; raw scores for cases in a group</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p150" block_type="eq-unl"><em>n</em><sub>Group</sub> &#61; number of cases in a group</p>
</box>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-11" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p151" block_type="nl-first">For each group, square each score and add them all up.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p152" block_type="nl-mid">For each group, add up all the scores, square the sum, and divide by the total number of cases.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p153" block_type="nl-mid">For each group, subtract the result of Step 2 from the result of Step 1.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p154" block_type="nl-last">Add together all the remainders from Step 3.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p155" block_type="txt-ni">As with the other sums of squares, <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-20">Table 10.6</link> has the components already prepared:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-12" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-28" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_346_04.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e_page_347" block_type="page_start">347</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p156" block_type="txt">Earlier in the chapter, it was stated that <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#43; <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>. Let&#8217;s see if that is true. <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> is 54.00 and <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> is 6.00. They sum to 60.00, which is what we calculated <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> to be. This is shown visually in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-29"><strong>Figure 10.9</strong></link>.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-29" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.9" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-29" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_09.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.9</phrase> Partitioning Total Sum of Squares for Maze Running Time Data</strong> <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> can be broken down into its component parts, <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> and <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>. Note that in this example the largest chunk of <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> is accounted for by <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p157" block_type="txt">Now that the degrees of freedom and sums of squares have been calculated, Dr. Chung can go on to calculate the <em>F</em> ratio. By organizing the sums of squares and the degrees of freedom into an ANOVA summary table, the <em>F</em> ratio will almost calculate itself.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p158" block_type="txt"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-30"><strong>Table 10.7</strong></link> is a template of a summary table for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA. It is important to note the order in which it is laid out&#8212;three rows and five columns. Always arrange a summary table for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA in exactly this way:</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-30" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.7" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-30" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_07.jpg"/>
</figure>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-12" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p159" block_type="bl-last">There is one row for each source of variability:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-13" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p160" block_type="bl_lvl2">Between-groups variability appears on the top row.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p161" block_type="bl_lvl2">Within-groups variability is on the middle row.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p162" block_type="bl_lvl2">Total variability goes on the bottom row.</p></li>
</list></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e_page_348" block_type="page_start">348</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-14" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p163" block_type="bl-last">The five columns, in order, tell:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-15" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p164" block_type="bl_lvl2">The source of variability (between, within, or total).</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p165" block_type="bl_lvl2">The sum of squares calculated for that source of variability.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p166" block_type="bl_lvl2">The degrees of freedom for that source of variability.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p167" block_type="bl_lvl2">What is called the &#8220;mean square&#8221; for that source of variability.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p168" block_type="bl_lvl2">The <em>F</em> ratio.</p></li>
</list></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p169" block_type="txt">Dr. Chung already has enough information to fill in the second and third columns. Mean square, the fourth column, sounds like something new, but it is a variance by another name. To calculate the mean square, one divides the sum of squares in a row by the degrees of freedom for that row.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p170" block_type="txt">To see how a mean square is a variance, let&#8217;s revisit the variance formula from <link href="corty3e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link> one more time:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-13" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-31" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_348_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p171" block_type="txt-ni">The numerator in this formula is the same as the sum of squares total. And, <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub> is <em>N</em> &#8211; 1. Thus, if mean square total were calculated, it would be exactly the same as the variance for all the cases. Analysis of variance really does analyze variances.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p172" block_type="txt">The only mean squares needed to complete a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA are between-groups mean square (<em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub>) and within-groups mean square (<em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub>). As the mean square total is not needed, the convention is not to calculate it and to leave the space blank where mean square total would go.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p173" block_type="txt">The formula for calculating the between-groups mean square is given in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-5">Equation 10.5</link>.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-5" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.5</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Formula for Between-Groups Mean Square, <em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub>, for Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-14" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-32" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_348_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p174" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; between-groups mean square</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p175" block_type="eq-unl"><em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; between-groups sum of squares</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p176" block_type="eq-unl"><em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; between-groups degrees of freedom</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e_page_349" block_type="page_start">349</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p177" block_type="txt">For the maze data, where <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 54.00 and <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 2, the between-groups mean square would be calculated:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-15" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-33" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_349_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p178" block_type="txt-ni"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-6">Equation 10.6</link> offers the formula for the within-groups mean square.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-6" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.6</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Formula for Within-Groups Mean Square, <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub>, for a Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-16" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-34" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_349_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p179" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; within-groups mean square</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p180" block_type="eq-unl"><em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; within-groups sum of squares</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p181" block_type="eq-unl"><em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; within-groups degrees of freedom</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p182" block_type="txt">For the maze data, <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 6.00 and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 7, so <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> would be calculated:</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-35" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-35" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_349_03.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p183" block_type="txt">Once the two mean squares are calculated, it is time to calculate the <em>F</em> ratio<em>.</em> <em>F</em> is the ratio of variability due to between-group factors and individual differences divided by the variability due to individual differences. <em>F</em> is calculated as shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-7">Equation 10.7</link>.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-7" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.7</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Formula for Calculating <em>F</em> for a Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-17" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-36" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_349_04.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p184" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>F</em> &#61; the <em>F</em> ratio</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p185" block_type="eq-unl"><em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; the between-groups mean square</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p186" block_type="eq-unl"><em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; the within-groups mean square</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e_page_350" block_type="page_start">350</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p187" block_type="txt">For the maze data, where <em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 27.00 and <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 0.86, <em>F</em> is calculated as</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-18" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-37" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_350_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p188" block_type="txt">The complete ANOVA summary table for the maze data is shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-38"><strong>Table 10.8</strong></link>. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-39"><strong>Table 10.9</strong></link> is a summary table that provides the organization and formulas for completing a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-38" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.8" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-38" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_08.jpg"/>
</figure>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-39" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.9" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-39" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_09.jpg"/>
</figure>
<box title="Worked Example 10.1" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx3-1" block_type="sr-exp-n">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p189" block_type="sr-ex-txt-ni">For practice with a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA, let&#8217;s explore how effective pain relievers like acetaminophen (Tylenol) and ibuprofen (Advil) are. Dr. Douglas, a sensory psychologist, wanted to see if medications such as these affected the pain threshold (how long it takes to perceive a stimulus as painful). Twelve male undergraduates volunteered for the study, and she randomly assigned them to three groups, one control group and two experimental groups, but tested each person individually. Each participant was given a pill&#8212;either a placebo, ibuprofen, or acetaminophen&#8212;waited an hour for the medication to take effect, then placed his hand in a bucket of ice water. As this was a test of pain threshold, he was told to remove his hand from the ice water as soon as it became painful. The researcher recorded the elapsed time, in seconds, as shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-40"><strong>Table 10.10</strong></link>. Note that this table has squared and summed scores so that the ANOVA computational formulas can be easily completed.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-40" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.10" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-40" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_10.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_351" block_type="page_start">351</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p190" block_type="sr_exp_txt"><link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-41"><strong>Figure 10.10</strong></link> shows what appears to be an effect of the pain relievers on the pain threshold. Compared to the placebo group, those using acetaminophen took longer on average to feel pain, and those given ibuprofen took even longer on average. It is necessary, of course, to conduct a hypothesis test to see if the effect is statistically significant and isn&#8217;t plausibly accounted for by sampling error.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-41" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.10" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-41" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_10.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.10</phrase> Mean Seconds to Mean Pain Threshold for Different Pain Relievers</strong> It appears that ibuprofen, and perhaps acetaminophen, raise the pain threshold compared to placebo. But, a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA has to be conducted to make sure that the effect is statistically significant.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p191" block_type="sr_exp_h4_txt"><phrase block_type="SR-EXP-h4-N-ni"><strong>Step 1</strong></phrase> <phrase data-block_type="SR-EXP-h4-T-ri"><strong>Pick a Test</strong></phrase></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p192" block_type="sr-ex-txt-ni">There are a number of conditions that lead to Dr. Douglas&#8217;s selection of between-subjects, one-way ANOVA as the appropriate test to analyze these data.</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-16" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p193" block_type="sr-exp-bl-first">There is one independent variable (factor), the type of drug.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p194" block_type="sr-exp-bl-first">This factor has three levels (placebo, ibuprofen, and acetaminophen), so there are three samples or groups.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p195" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">The cases were randomly assigned to the groups, so the samples are independent samples.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p196" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">The dependent variable, number of seconds to pain threshold, is measured at the ratio level so means can be calculated for each group.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e_page_352" block_type="page_start">352</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p197" block_type="sr_exp_h4_txt"><phrase block_type="SR-EXP-h4-N-ni"><strong>Step 2</strong></phrase> <phrase data-block_type="SR-EXP-h4-T-ri"><strong>Check the Assumptions</strong></phrase></p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-17" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p198" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">Random samples: The samples are made up of male, college-student volunteers, so they are not random samples from the human population. The random samples assumption is violated, but it is a robust assumption so the researcher can proceed. She&#8217;ll just have to be careful about the population to which she generalizes the results.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p199" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">Independence of cases: Each participant was in the study only once. Plus, each participant was tested individually, uninfluenced by the other participants. This assumption was not violated.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p200" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">Normality: Researchers are commonly willing to assume that psychological variables, like pain threshold, are normally distributed. So, this assumption is not violated.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p201" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">Homogeneity of variance: All the standard deviations (4.04, 5.48, and 4.76, from <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-40">Table 10.10</link>) are very similar, so the amount of variability in each population seems about equal.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p202" block_type="sr_exp_txt">With no nonrobust assumptions violated, Dr. Douglas can proceed with the planned between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p203" block_type="sr_exp_h4_txt"><phrase block_type="SR-EXP-h4-N-ni"><strong>Step 3</strong></phrase> <phrase data-block_type="SR-EXP-h4-T-ri"><strong>List the Hypotheses</strong></phrase></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p204" block_type="sr-exp-eq"><em>H</em><sub>0</sub>: &#956;<sub>1</sub> &#61; &#956;<sub>2</sub> &#61; &#956;<sub>3</sub>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p205" block_type="sr-exp-eq"><em>H</em><sub>1</sub>: At least one population mean is different from the others.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p206" block_type="sr_exp_h4_txt"><phrase block_type="SR-EXP-h4-N-ni"><strong>Step 4</strong></phrase> <phrase data-block_type="SR-EXP-h4-T-ri"><strong>Set the Decision Rule</strong></phrase></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p207" block_type="sr-ex-txt-ni">In order to find the critical value of <em>F,</em> Dr. Douglas needs to know the degrees of freedom for the numerator (<em>df</em><sub>Between</sub>) and for the denominator (<em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>). To do so, she uses <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-1">Equation 10.1</link>:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p208" block_type="sr-exp-eq"><em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; <em>k</em> &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p209" block_type="sr-exp-eq">&#61; 3 &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p210" block_type="sr-exp-eq">&#61; 2</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p211" block_type="sr-exp-eq"><em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; <em>N</em> &#8211; <em>k</em></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p212" block_type="sr-exp-eq">&#61; 12 &#8211; 3</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p213" block_type="sr-exp-eq">&#61; 9</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p214" block_type="sr-exp-eq"><em>df</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; <em>N</em> &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p215" block_type="sr-exp-eq">&#61; 12 &#8211; 1</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p216" block_type="sr-exp-eq">&#61; 11</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_353" block_type="page_start">353</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p217" block_type="sr_exp_txt">Looking at the &#945; &#61; .05 version of <link href="corty3e_app1_1.html#corty3e-app1-fig-10">Appendix Table 4</link>&#8212;at the intersection of the column for 2 degrees of freedom in the numerator and the row for 9 degrees of freedom in the denominator&#8212;she finds <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> is 4.256. Here is the decision rule:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-18" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p218" block_type="sr-exp-bl-first">If <em>F</em> &#8805; 4.256, reject <em>H</em><sub>0</sub>.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p219" block_type="sr-exp-bl-first">If <em>F</em> &#60; 4.256, fail to reject <em>H</em><sub>0</sub>.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p220" block_type="sr_exp_h4_txt"><phrase block_type="SR-EXP-h4-N-ni"><strong>Step 5</strong></phrase> <phrase data-block_type="SR-EXP-h4-T-ri"><strong>Calculate the Test Statistic</strong></phrase></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p221" block_type="sr-ex-txt-ni">Dr. Douglas&#8217;s first step on the path to <em>F</em> is to calculate <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>, using <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-2">Equation 10.2</link> and values from <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-40">Table 10.10</link>:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-19" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-42" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_353_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p222" block_type="sr_exp_txt">Next, she calculates <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> following <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-3">Equation 10.3</link>:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-20" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-43" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_353_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p223" block_type="sr_exp_txt">Finally, using <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-4">Equation 10.4</link>, she calculates <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-21" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-44" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_353_03.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e_page_354" block_type="page_start">354</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p224" block_type="sr_exp_txt">As a check that she has done the math correctly, she adds together <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> (62.00) and <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> (207.00) to make sure that they sum to sum of squares total (269.00). They do. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-45"><strong>Figure 10.11</strong></link> shows this visually.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-45" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.11" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-45" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_11.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.11</phrase> Partitioning Total Sum of Squares for Mean Pain Threshold Data</strong> <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> can be broken down into its component parts, <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> and <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>. Note that the largest chunk of <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> is accounted for by <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p225" block_type="sr_exp_txt">The final step is to complete an ANOVA summary table for the pain threshold data. The degrees of freedom and sums of squares already calculated can be used to start to fill in the summary table. Then, following the guidelines in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-39">Table 10.9</link>, Dr. Douglas completes the ANOVA summary table (see <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-46"><strong>Table 10.11</strong></link>), finding <em>F</em> =1.35. In the next section, we&#8217;ll learn how to interpret the results.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-46" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.11" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-46" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_11.jpg"/>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="corty3e_page_355" block_type="page_start">355</p>
<box title="Practice Problems 10.2 " numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx2-2" block_type="sr-h">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p226" block_type="sr-h1"><strong>Apply Your Knowledge</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p227" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.5</phrase> Select the correct test for this example: A gerontologist wants to determine which exercise program, yoga or stretching, leads to greater limberness in elderly people. He uses a ratio-level range-of-motion test to measure limberness and randomly assigns elderly people to receive either eight weeks of yoga or eight weeks of stretching.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p228" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.6</phrase> Select the correct test for this example: A human factors psychologist is comparing three different adhesives used in sealing cereal boxes to see which one is easiest to open. He obtained 90 consumers, randomly assigned each participant to open one cereal box, and measured how long it took to open the box. Thirty of the boxes were sealed with Adhesive A, 30 with Adhesive B, and 30 with Adhesive C.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p229" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.7</phrase> If the numerator <em>df</em> for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA are 4 and the denominator <em>df</em> are 20, what is the decision rule if &#945; &#61; .05?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p230" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.8</phrase> If a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA has 32 cases randomly assigned to four equally sized groups, what are <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub>, <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>, and <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p231" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.9</phrase> Here are data on an interval-level variable for three independent samples. Prepare this table so that it would be ready for use in computing sums of squares. (Do not compute the sums of squares.)</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table2" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 1</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 2</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 3</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">16</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">12</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">13</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">17</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">14</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">15</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">20</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">18</phrase></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p232" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.10</phrase> Given the data in the table below, calculate (a) <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>, (b) <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>, and (c) <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>.</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table1" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-STRHD"><strong>Group 1</strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-STRHD"><strong>Group 2</strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-STRHD"><strong>Group 3</strong></phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">16</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">256</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">19</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">361</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">26</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">676</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">18</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">324</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">20</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">400</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">22</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">484</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">14</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">196</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">22</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">484</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">25</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">625</phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Grand</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">18</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">324</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">24</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">576</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">27</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">729</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-STRHD">&#8721;</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">66.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">1,100.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">85.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">1,821.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">100.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2,514.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">251.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">5,435.00</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-STRHD"><strong>n</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">12</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"></phrase></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p233" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.11</phrase> Given <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 3, <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 12, <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 15, <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 716.00, <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 228.00, and <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 944.00, complete an ANOVA summary table.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec1-3" block_type="h1" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="355">
<section-metadata><section-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">10.3</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Interpreting Between-Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p234" block_type="txt-ni">The interpretation of a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA starts the same way it did for <em>t</em> tests, addressing questions of whether the null hypothesis was rejected and how big the effect is. After that, the interpretation answers a different question, where the effect is found.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p235" block_type="txt">Why is there a need to worry about where the effect is? This question didn&#8217;t have to be addressed for a <em>t</em> test because in a <em>t</em> test just two groups exist. If the results of a <em>t</em> test were statistically significant, it was clear that the mean of Group 1 was different from the mean of Group 2. However, there can be more than two groups in an ANOVA. If the results of the ANOVA are statistically significant, then all that is known is that the mean of at least one group is different from at least one other group. If there are three groups, the mean of Group 1 could differ from the mean of Group 2, the mean of Group 1 could differ from the mean of Group 3, or the mean of Group 2 could differ from the mean of Group 3. It is also possible that two of the mean of the three pairs could differ or that all three pairs could differ. This is why it&#8217;s important to address the question of where the effect is when interpreting a statistically significant ANOVA.</p>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec2-5" block_type="h2" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="356">
<section-metadata><section-title>Was the Null Hypothesis Rejected?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e_page_356" block_type="page_start">356</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p236" block_type="txt-ni">Dr. Chung&#8217;s maze study compared rats that expected to find different foods in the goal box of a maze. Ten rats were assigned to three groups&#8212;one that expected to find low-calorie food in the goal box, one that expected medium-calorie food, and one that expected high-calorie food. The rats expecting low-calorie food took 31 seconds from start box to goal box, the rats expecting medium-calorie food took 28 seconds, and the rats expecting high-calorie food took 25 seconds. Dr. Chung had determined <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> &#61; 4.737 and formulated the decision rule:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-19" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p237" block_type="bl-first">If <em>F</em> &#8805; 4.737, reject the null hypothesis.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p238" block_type="bl-last">If <em>F</em> &#60; 4.737, fail to reject the null hypothesis.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p239" block_type="txt">As shown in the ANOVA summary table, <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-38">Table 10.8</link>, <em>F</em> &#61; 31.40 for the maze data. Applying the decision rule, it is clear that 31.40 is greater than or equal to 4.737, and <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-47"><strong>Figure 10.12</strong></link> shows how the observed value of <em>F</em> falls in the rare zone. This means that the null hypothesis is rejected and the alternative hypothesis accepted. This leads to the conclusion that at least one of the three groups&#8212;rats expecting low-calorie food, rats expecting medium-calorie food, or rats expecting high-calorie food&#8212;differs from at least one of the others in terms of the mean time it takes to get to the food. It is not yet clear where the difference lies, so the best interpretation Dr. Chung can make at present is: &#8220;The results of the between-subjects, one-way ANOVA were statistically significant [<em>F</em>(2, 7) &#61; 31.40, <em>p</em> &#60; .05], indicating that there is a statistically significant difference in the time it takes to get from the start box to the goal box depending on the calorie content of the food a rat expects to find.&#8221;</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-47" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.12" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-47" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_12.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.12</phrase> Determining Whether the Observed Value of the Test Statistic Falls in the Rare Zone or the Common Zone for the Maze Study</strong> The observed value of the test statistic, <em>F</em> &#61; 31.40, falls in the rare zone, so the null hypothesis is rejected.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_357" block_type="page_start">357</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p240" block_type="txt">Dr. Chung used APA format in reporting the results of the analysis of variance. APA format provides five pieces of information:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-20" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p241" block_type="nl-first"><em>F</em> indicates that an <em>F</em> test, an analysis of variance, was used.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p242" block_type="nl-mid">The numbers in parentheses, 2 and 7, are the degrees of freedom for <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>, the numerator of the <em>F</em> ratio, and for <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>, the denominator of the <em>F</em> ratio. By adding these two numbers together and adding 1, it is possible to find the sample size:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p243" block_type="eq"><em>N</em> &#61; 2 &#43; 7 &#43; 1 &#61; 10</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p244" block_type="nl-mid">31.40 is the observed (calculated) value of the test statistic.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p245" block_type="nl-mid">.05 reveals that alpha was set at .05 and there is a 5&#37; chance of making a Type I error.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p246" block_type="nl-last"><em>p</em> &#60; .05 indicates that the null hypothesis was rejected. It means that an <em>F</em> value of 31.40 is a rare occurrence (it happens less than 5&#37; of the time) when the null hypothesis is true.</p></li>
</list>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec2-6" block_type="h2" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="357">
<section-metadata><section-title>How Big Is the Effect?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p247" block_type="txt-ni">The second question to be addressed in interpreting an ANOVA is how big the <em>overall</em> effect is. That is, how much impact does the independent variable have on the dependent variable? For the maze data, this involves asking how much impact the three different types of food (low-, medium-, and high-calorie) have on the time it takes to run the maze.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p248" block_type="txt">Once again, <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> will be used. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-8">Equation 10.8</link> shows how to calculate <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>, the percentage of variability in the outcome variable that is accounted for by group status.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-8" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.8</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Formula for <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>, the Percentage of Variability in the Dependent Variable Accounted for by the Explanatory Variable</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-22" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-48" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_357_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p249" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> &#61; the percentage of variability in the dependent variable that is accounted for by the explanatory variable</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p250" block_type="eq-unl"><em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; between-groups sum of squares (<link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-3">Equation 10.3</link>)</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p251" block_type="eq-unl"><em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; total sum of squares (<link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-2">Equation 10.2</link>)</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p252" block_type="txt">This formula says that <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> is calculated as the between-groups sum of squares divided by the total sum of squares. Then, to turn it into a percentage, the ratio is multiplied by 100. These calculations reveal the percentage of total variability in the scores that is accounted for by the treatment effect. For the maze data, these calculations would lead to the conclusion that <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> &#61; 90&#37;:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-23" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-49" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_357_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e_page_358" block_type="page_start">358</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p253" block_type="txt-ni">By Cohen&#8217;s standards, an <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> of 90&#37; is a huge effect. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-50"><strong>Figure 10.13</strong></link> is a visual demonstration of how big an effect this is. Here is what Dr. Chung&#8217;s interpretation would look like for the maze data now that <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> is known:</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-50" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.13" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-50" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_13.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.13</phrase> Percentage of Variability in Time to Run the Maze Scores That Is Accounted for by Type of Food in Goal Box</strong> 90&#37; of the variability in time it takes for rats to run the maze is accounted for by the type of food they expect to find in the goal box. Only 10&#37; of the variability remains, to be accounted for by other factors such as individual differences.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p254" block_type="sr_exp_txt_v1_ni">The results of the one-way ANOVA were statistically significant [<em>F</em>(2, 7) &#61; 31.40, <em>p</em> &#60; .05], indicating that the time it takes a hungry rat to run a maze is affected by the type of food it expects to find in the goal box. When all the rats are of the same age and from the same strain, as they were here, then the calorie content of the food in the goal box has a very large effect on the speed with which the animal travels the maze. In fact, the type of food in the goal box explains 90&#37; of the variability in running speed.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p255" block_type="txt">Here&#8217;s a heads up for future chapters and for reading results sections in psychology articles&#8212;there&#8217;s another measure of effect size for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA that is calculated exactly the same way as <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>, but is called something different. It is called &#8220;eta squared&#8221; and abbreviated &#951;<sup>2</sup>. It is calculated the same way as <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> and provides the same information, how much of the variability in the dependent variable is explained by the independent variable.</p>
<box title="A Common Question" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx1-2" block_type="bx-1-h">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p256" block_type="bx1-que"><strong>Q</strong> How is &#951; pronounced?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p257" block_type="bx1-ans"><strong>A</strong> &#951; is the lowercase version of the Greek letter eta and there is no consensus on how it should be pronounced. I have heard &#8220;eat-uh,&#8221; &#8220;etta,&#8221; and &#8220;ey-tuh&#8221; as in &#8220;hey.&#8221; Whichever one you choose, just say it with confidence and you&#8217;ll be fine.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec2-7" block_type="h2" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="358">
<section-metadata><section-title>Where Is the Effect?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p258" block_type="txt-ni">So far, Dr. Chung knows that the goal affects running time and how much variability is explained, but he doesn&#8217;t know where the effect occurs. Is the 3-second difference between the mean of low-calorie time and the mean of medium-calorie time a statistically significant one? Or, does it take the 6-second difference between low-calorie and high-calorie goals to be statistically significant?</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_359" block_type="page_start">359</p>
<box numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-exp1-3" block_type="mn1">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p259" block_type="mn-ext-ni"><em>Post-hoc tests are meant to be used only</em> after <em>a statistically significant</em> F <em>ratio has been found.</em></p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p260" block_type="txt">The <em>F</em> ratio, which was statistically significant, reveals that at least one pair of means has a statistically significant difference, but it doesn&#8217;t tell which one or which ones. For that, a <em>post-hoc</em> test is needed. &#8220;Post-hoc&#8221; is Latin for &#8220;after this&#8221; and post-hoc tests are meant to be used only <em>after</em> a statistically significant <em>F</em> ratio has been found. Post-hoc tests are mathematically designed to allow multiple comparisons to be made while keeping alpha at the desired level.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p261" block_type="txt">There are a wide variety of post-hoc tests with cool names like the Scheff&#233;, the Newman-Keuls, and the Bonferroni-Dunn. Post-hoc tests vary in terms of what type of error they are more likely to make, a Type I error or a Type II error. No post-hoc test can guarantee avoiding a mistake. Compared to each other, some post-hoc tests are more likely to say that there is a statistically significant difference between means that don&#8217;t differ (Type I error). Other post-hoc tests are more likely to find no statistically significant difference when a difference exists (Type II error).</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p262" block_type="txt">The test taught here, the Tukey <em>HSD,</em> is the latter type, what is called a conservative test. If it finds a statistically significant difference between a pair of means, then the population means probably really are different. Which is why <em>HSD</em> stands for &#8220;honestly significant difference.&#8221; However, there is a cost to this conservatism: the <em>HSD</em> has less statistical power and so may overlook a pair of means that are different.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p263" block_type="txt">The Tukey <em>HSD</em> works by calculating an <em>HSD</em> value, which is the minimum difference needed between two means in order for the difference to be considered statistically significant. If the observed difference between a pair of means is greater than or equal to the <em>HSD</em> value, then the researcher can conclude that there is a statistically significant difference between the two groups. For example, the mean for the low-calorie group was 31 seconds and for the medium-calorie group it was 28 seconds. There is a 3.00-second difference between the mean of these two groups. If the <em>HSD</em> value were, say, 2.50, then the difference between the mean of these two groups would be a statistically significant one. This is the case because the observed difference, 3.00, met or exceeded the <em>HSD</em> value of 2.50.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p264" block_type="txt">The formula to calculate <em>HSD</em> is shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-9">Equation 10.9</link>. In order to apply that formula, one needs a value called <em>q.</em> Values of <em>q</em> can be found in <link href="corty3e_app1_1.html#corty3e-app1-fig-18">Appendix Table 5</link>, a part of which is shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-51"><strong>Table 10.12.</strong></link></p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-51" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.12" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-51" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_12.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_360" block_type="page_start">360</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p265" block_type="txt">There are <em>q</em> tables for &#945; &#61; .05 and &#945; &#61; .01, for a 5&#37; and a 1&#37; chance of making a Type I error. The <em>q</em> values are found at the intersections of rows and columns.</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-21" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p266" block_type="bl-first">The columns represent different values of <em>k,</em> the number of groups being compared in the ANOVA.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p267" block_type="bl-last">The columns represent within-groups degrees of freedom, <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p268" block_type="txt-ni">For the maze data, there are three groups and within-groups degrees of freedom are 7. The <em>q</em> value of 4.17 is found at the intersection of the column where <em>k</em> &#61; 3 with the row where <em>df</em> &#61; 7.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx6-9" block_type="eq-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="sec_num">Equation 10.9</phrase> <phrase block_type="sec_title">Formula to Calculate Tukey <em>HSD</em> Value for a Post-Hoc Test for Between Subjects, One-Way ANOVA</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-24" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-52" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_360_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p269" block_type="eq-txt-ni">where <em>HSD</em> &#61; value by which, if two means differ, the difference is statistically significant</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p270" block_type="eq-unl"><em>q</em> &#61; value of <em>q,</em> from <link href="corty3e_app1_1.html#corty3e-app1-fig-18">Appendix Table 5</link></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p271" block_type="eq-unl"><em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> (from ANOVA summary table)</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p272" block_type="eq-unl"><em>n</em> &#61; sample size for the smallest group</p>
</box>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p273" block_type="txt">To calculate <em>HSD,</em> one needs to know <em>q,</em> <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub>, and <em>n:</em></p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-22" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p274" block_type="bl-first">From <link href="corty3e_app1_1.html#corty3e-app1-fig-18">Appendix Table 5</link>, it is known that <em>q</em> &#61; 4.17.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p275" block_type="bl-mid">Referring back to the ANOVA summary table for the maze data (<link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-30">Table 10.7</link>), <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 0.86.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p276" block_type="bl-last">The only missing piece is <em>n,</em> the sample size for the smallest group. In <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-11">Table 10.3</link>, where the maze data were first presented, it can be seen that the smallest group has three cases, so <em>n</em> &#61; 3. (Tukey&#8217;s <em>HSD</em> was designed to be used when all sample sizes are equal. When sample sizes are unequal, using the smallest sample size makes the <em>HSD</em> value larger, which keeps the test conservative.)</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p277" block_type="txt-ni">With all the parts in place, the <em>HSD</em> value is calculated as</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-25" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-53" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_360_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e_page_361" block_type="page_start">361</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p278" block_type="txt">The <em>HSD</em> value is 2.23. Any two means that differ by at least 2.23 seconds are honestly significantly different. Here are the three sample means:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-23" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p279" block_type="bl-first">Group 1: Expecting low-calorie food in the goal box &#61; 31.00 seconds</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p280" block_type="bl-mid">Group 2: Expecting medium-calorie food in the goal box &#61; 28.00 seconds</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p281" block_type="bl-last">Group 3: Expecting high-calorie food in the goal box &#61; 25.00 seconds</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p282" block_type="txt-ni">Here are the comparisons:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-24" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p283" block_type="bl-first">Group 1 vs. Group 2: There is a 3.00-second difference between the mean of Group 1 and the mean of Group 2. 3.00 &#8805; 2.23, so this is a statistically significant difference.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p284" block_type="bl-mid">Group 1 vs. Group 3: There is a 6.00-second difference between the mean of Group 1 and the mean of Group 3. 6.00 &#8805; 2.23, so this is a statistically significant difference.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p285" block_type="bl-last">Group 2 vs. Group 3: There is a 3.00-second difference between the mean of Group 2 and the mean of Group 3. 3.00 &#8805; 2.23, so this is a statistically significant difference.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p286" block_type="txt">Once a researcher knows whether a difference is statistically significant, he or she needs to think about the direction of the difference. As with <em>t</em> tests, the actual sample means can be used to determine the direction of the difference. Here are Dr. Chung&#8217;s conclusions:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-25" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p287" block_type="bl-first">Group 1 vs. Group 2: Expecting medium-calorie food compared to low-calorie food leads to rats taking significantly less time to travel through the maze. That is, the medium-calorie rats ran through the maze statistically more quickly on average.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p288" block_type="bl-mid">Group 1 vs. Group 3: There&#8217;s a significant difference between expecting low-calorie food and expecting medium-calorie food, so it&#8217;s not surprising that a similar difference exists between expecting low-calorie food and expecting high-calorie food. Rats expecting high-calorie food were statistically faster on average than rats expecting low-calorie food.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p289" block_type="bl-last">Group 2 vs. Group 3: Rats expecting high-calorie food were statistically faster on average than rats expecting medium-calorie food.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p290" block_type="txt">A statistically significant ANOVA reveals that at least one pair of population means differs. Now after the post-hoc test, Dr. Chung knows which pairs differ and what the differences mean. His challenge is to summarize the findings. He could report that the mean of Group 1 differs from the mean of Group 2 and that the mean of Group 1 differs from the mean of Group 3, and so forth, but that would be a focus on the trees, not the forest. Interpretations are more useful if they find a pattern in the results. Dr. Chung&#8217;s findings could be summarized by saying that rats, this strain of rats at least, appear able to figure out that different foods have different caloric contents and, when hungry, are more motivated to seek nutritionally richer foods.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p291" block_type="txt">With all three interpretation questions addressed&#8212;Was the null hypothesis rejected? How big is the effect? Where is the effect?&#8212;Dr. Chung is ready to write a four-point interpretation that (1) tells what the study was about, (2) presents the main results, (3) explains what the results mean, and (4) makes suggestions for future research:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p292" block_type="sr_exp_txt_v1_ni">In this study, rats were exposed to three different types of food (low-calorie, medium-calorie, and high-calorie) in the goal box while learning a maze. After learning the maze, they were made hungry, randomly assigned to three groups, and timed while they ran the maze. The three groups expected to find different foods in the goal box: low-calorie, medium-calorie, or high-calorie. There was a statistically significant decrease in mean time, that is, an increase in mean speed, as the caloric content of the food increased [<em>F</em>(2, 7) &#61; 31.40, <em>p</em> &#60; .05]. Time decreased from a mean of 31.00 seconds for the rats expecting low-calorie food to 28.00 seconds for those expecting medium-calorie food and to 25.00 seconds for the ones expecting high-calorie food. The effect of caloric content on speed in this study was quite dramatic, accounting for 90&#37; of the variability in speed. This is probably an overestimate of the effect of caloric content as all rats were from the same strain and were the same age.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_362" block_type="page_start">362</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p293" block_type="sr_exp_txt_v1_ni">These results suggest that this strain of rats is able to discriminate the caloric content of food and that, when they are hungry, they are more motivated to seek nutritionally richer food. This motivation makes sense for increasing the likelihood of survival in lean times. An alternative explanation for the results is that the richer-calorie foods tasted better and that rats hurry to food if it tastes good. Future research should be sure to control for food taste. Future research should also employ different strains of rats.</p>
<box title="Worked Example 10.2" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx3-2" block_type="sr-exp-n">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p294" block_type="sr-ex-txt-ni">For practice in interpretation, let&#8217;s return to Dr. Douglas&#8217;s data from the study of over-the-counter pain relievers (ibuprofen and acetaminophen) on pain threshold. In that study, 12 male undergraduates were randomly assigned by a sensory psychologist to take a placebo, ibuprofen, or acetaminophen. They then placed their hands in ice water until they felt pain. The participants who received placebos kept their hands in ice water for an average of 17.50 seconds, the ibuprofen participants for 23.00 seconds, and the acetaminophen participants for 21.00 seconds. <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> was 4.256 and the ANOVA summary table is reprinted here (see <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-54"><strong>Table 10.13</strong></link>).</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-54" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.13" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-54" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_13.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p295" block_type="sr_exp_txt"><em>Was the null hypothesis rejected?</em> From the ANOVA summary table (<link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-54">Table 10.13</link>), it is clear that the observed value of <em>F</em> is 1.35. 1.35 is less than 4.256, <em>F<sub>cv</sub>,</em> so the null hypothesis was not rejected. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-55"><strong>Figure 10.14</strong></link> shows how the observed value of <em>F</em> falls in the common zone. With these data, Dr. Douglas does not have enough evidence to state that any one of these three groups differs from another in terms of the mean pain threshold. In APA format, she would write the results as</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-55" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.14" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-55" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_14.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.14</phrase> Determining Whether the Observed Value of the Test Statistic Falls in the Rare Zone or the Common Zone for the Pain Threshold Study</strong> The observed value of the test statistic, <em>F</em> &#61; 1.35, falls in the common zone, so we fail to reject the null hypothesis.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p296" block_type="sr-exp-eq"><em>F</em>(2, 9) &#61; 1.35, <em>p</em> > .05</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-26" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p297" block_type="sr-exp-bl-first"><em>F</em> tells the reader that an analysis of variance, also known as an <em>F</em> test, was done.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_363" block_type="page_start">363</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p298" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">The 2 and 9 in the parentheses are the numerator and denominator degrees of freedom. These are <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>. If they are added together and 1 is added, that gives <em>N.</em></p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p299" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">1.35 is the value of <em>F</em> that Dr. Douglas calculated.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p300" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">The .05 is the alpha level that had been selected.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p301" block_type="sr-exp-bl-last">The <em>p</em> > .05 means that a result like <em>F</em> &#61; 1.35 is a common one when the null hypothesis is true, as under those conditions it occurs more than 5&#37; of the time. The sensory psychologist has failed to reject the null hypothesis.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p302" block_type="sr_exp_txt"><em>How big is the effect?</em> <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-5">Equation 10.5</link> is used to calculate the effect size, <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>, the percentage of variability in the dependent variable (seconds to pain threshold) that is accounted for by the independent variable (type of painkiller). To use the equation, two values, <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> (62.00) and <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> (269.00), are obtained from the ANOVA summary table:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-26" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-56" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_363_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p303" block_type="sr_exp_txt">An <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> of 23&#37; is close to a large effect, according to Cohen. This gives Dr. Douglas two conflicting pieces of information:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-27" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p304" block_type="sr-exp-bl-first">Not enough evidence exists to say there is an effect.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p305" block_type="sr-exp-bl-mid">However, the effect seems to be large.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e_page_364" block_type="page_start">364</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p306" block_type="sr_exp_txt">One way to reconcile these two conflicting pieces of information is to look at the possibility of a Type II error. Type II errors occur when a researcher fails to find statistically significant evidence of an effect that really does exist. That possibility can&#8217;t be ruled out here. When interpreting such a situation, the researcher should point out the possibility and suggest that the study be replicated with a larger sample size. Larger sample sizes give tests more power and so increase the likelihood of being able to find an effect when it does exist.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p307" block_type="sr_exp_txt"><em>Where is the effect?</em> Post-hoc tests are designed to be conducted only when the null hypothesis is rejected. In this study, the null hypothesis was not rejected. This means there is not enough evidence that an effect exists, so there is no reason to try to find where the effect is.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p308" block_type="sr_exp_txt"><em>Putting it all together.</em> Here&#8217;s Dr. Douglas&#8217;s four-point interpretation for the pain threshold study. She reveals what the study was about, identifies its main results, interprets them, and makes suggestions for future research.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p309" block_type="sr_exp_txt_v1_ni">Analysis of data for a study comparing the impact of placebo, ibuprofen, and acetaminophen on pain threshold found no evidence that either of the over-the-counter pain relievers had any impact on the threshold for perceiving pain. There was no statistically significant difference in the mean time it took participants to perceive pain when their hands were in ice water [<em>F</em>(2, 9) &#61; 1.35, <em>p</em> > .05]. There was some evidence that medication may have an impact, but the small sample size (<em>N</em> =12) meant the study did not have enough power to detect it. In order to determine if these over-the-counter pain relievers have an impact on pain threshold, the study should be replicated with a larger sample size.</p>
</box>
<box title="Practice Problems 10.3" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx2-3" block_type="sr-h">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p310" block_type="sr-h1"><strong>Apply Your Knowledge</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p311" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.12</phrase> Given &#945; &#61; .05, <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> &#61; 2.690, <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 4, <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 30, and <em>F</em> &#61; 7.37, write the results in APA format.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p312" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.13</phrase> Given <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 1,827.50 and <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 4,631.50, (a) calculate <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> and (b) comment on the size of the effect.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p313" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.14</phrase> Four groups are being compared in a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA. Each group has 10 cases. <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 77.89 and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 36. The <em>F</em> ratio was statistically significant with &#945; &#61; .05.</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-28" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p314" block_type="sr-que-ll">Use this information to complete a post-hoc test comparing <em>M</em><sub>1</sub> &#61; 29.00 and <em>M</em><sub>2</sub> &#61; 18.00; interpret the difference between the two population means.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p315" block_type="sr-que-ll">Use this information to complete a post-hoc test comparing <em>M</em><sub>1</sub> &#61; 29.00 and <em>M</em><sub>3</sub> &#61; 22.00; interpret the difference between the two population means.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p316" block_type="sr-que-nl"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.15</phrase> An industrial/organizational psychologist wanted to investigate the effect of different management styles on employee performance. She obtained 27 employees at a large company and randomly assigned them, in equal-sized groups, to be supervised by managers who believed in motivating employees by using (a) rewards for good performance, (b) punishment for poor performance, or (c) a mixture of rewards and punishments. No nonrobust assumptions of a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA were violated. One year later, she recorded how much of a raise (as a percentage) each employee received. She believed that employees who did better work would receive bigger raises. The employees supervised by managers who believed in using rewards saw a mean raise of 8&#37;, those supervised by managers who believed in using punishment had a mean raise of 5&#37;, and those supervised by managers who used a mixture of rewards and punishment had a mean raise of 7&#37;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p317" block_type="sr-x-txt-ni">A between-subjects, one-way ANOVA was used to analyze the results. The results were statistically significant. Given the ANOVA summary table, <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> &#61; 30.43&#37; and <em>HSD</em> &#61; 2.35, write a four-point interpretation.</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table3" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Source of Variability</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Sum of Squares</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Degrees of Freedom</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Mean Square</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>F</em> ratio</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-SIDHD"><strong>Between groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">42.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">21.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">5.25</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-SIDHD"><strong>Within groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">96.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">24</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4.00</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-SIDHD"><strong>Total</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">138.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">26</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</box>
<p id="corty3e_page_365" block_type="page_start">365</p>
<box title="Application Demonstration" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx3-3" block_type="sr-x-h">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p318" block_type="sr-x-txt-ni">America is a land of movers. If we don&#8217;t like where we&#8217;re living, if we think the grass is greener somewhere else, we just pull up our stakes and go. Are salaries for psychologists consistent throughout the United States or do some areas have higher or lower salaries? If so, this information could guide a recent graduate&#8217;s decision about where to seek employment.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p319" block_type="sr-x-txt">The Census Bureau divides the United States into four regions: the Northeast, Midwest, South, and West. Four states from each region were randomly selected and the mean salary for &#8220;clinical, counseling, and school psychologists&#8221; was obtained from a Bureau of Labor Statistics website for each state. Salaries were recorded in thousands of dollars; &#36;79.52, for example, means &#36;79,520. Recording the values this way keeps the sums of squares from becoming unwieldy numbers in the hundreds of millions. The mean salaries for the four regions (Northeast <strong>&#61;</strong> &#36;77.73, Midwest &#61; &#36;63.55, West &#61; &#36;68.83, and South &#61; &#36;61.37) are seen in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-57"><strong>Figure 10.15.</strong></link></p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-57" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.15" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-57" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_15.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.15</phrase> Mean Salary for Psychologists by Census Region: Two Different Pictures</strong> The mean salary for clinical, counseling, and school psychologists is highest in the Northeast and lowest in the South. Whether the differences among regions look significant or not depends on how the graph is drawn. The two graphs here differ only in the scale on the <em>Y</em>-axis.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p320" block_type="txt">The top panel in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-57">Figure 10.15</link> shows some slight differences in salary by region. Based on this graph, it seems unlikely that there are any statistically significant differences. The bottom panel in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-57">Figure 10.15</link>, where the <em>y</em>-axis doesn&#8217;t start at zero, does make it look like there are significant differences by region. As mentioned in <link href="corty3e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link>, a graph is a subjective interpretation of the data. The question of whether there are differences in mean salary is best resolved in an objective manner with a significance test.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_366" block_type="page_start">366</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p321" block_type="h4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 1</strong></phrase> <strong>Pick a Test.</strong> There are four samples, they are independent, and the dependent variable is measured at the ratio level, so the test should be a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p322" block_type="h4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 2</strong></phrase> <strong>Check the Assumptions.</strong></p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-29" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p323" block_type="sr-x-bl-first">The random samples assumption is not violated. Cases were randomly selected from their populations.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p324" block_type="sr-x-bl-mid">The independence of observations assumption is not violated. Each state (case) is measured only once.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p325" block_type="sr-x-bl-mid">The normality assumption might be violated. The populations are not large. For example, there are only nine states in the Northeast. With such a small population, it is unlikely to be normally distributed. But, this assumption is robust.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p326" block_type="sr-x-bl-last">The homogeneity of variance assumption is not violated. All standard deviations are comparable.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p327" block_type="h4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 3</strong></phrase> <strong>List the Hypotheses.</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p328" block_type="sr-x-eq"><em>H</em><sub>0</sub>: &#956;<sub>1</sub> &#61; &#956;<sub>2</sub> &#61; &#956;<sub>3</sub> &#61; &#956;<sub>4</sub>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p329" block_type="sr-x-eq"><em>H</em><sub>1</sub>: At least one population mean differs from the others.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p330" block_type="h4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 4</strong></phrase> <strong>Set the Decision Rule.</strong> First, find the numerator, denominator, and total degrees of freedom:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p331" block_type="sr-x-eq">Numerator degrees of freedom &#61; <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; <em>k</em> &#8722; 1 &#61; 4 &#8722; 1 &#61; 3</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p332" block_type="sr-x-eq">Denominator degrees of freedom &#61; <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; <em>N</em> &#8722; <em>k</em> &#61; 16 &#8722; 4 &#61; 12</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p333" block_type="sr-x-eq">Total degrees of freedom &#61; <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; <em>N</em> &#8722; 1 &#61; 16 &#8722; 1 &#61; 15</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p334" block_type="sr-x-txt-ni">Next, set the alpha level:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p335" block_type="sr-x-eq">&#945; &#61; .05 because willing to have a 5&#37; chance of making a Type I error</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p336" block_type="sr-x-txt-ni">Then, use the degrees of freedom and alpha level to find the critical value of <em>F</em> in <link href="corty3e_app1_1.html#corty3e-app1-fig-10">Appendix Table 4</link>:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p337" block_type="sr-x-eq"><em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> &#61; 3.490</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p338" block_type="sr-x-txt-ni">Then, set the decision rule:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-30" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p339" block_type="sr-x-bl-first">If <em>F</em> &#8805; 3.490, reject <em>H</em><sub>0</sub>.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p340" block_type="sr-x-bl-last">If <em>F</em> &#60; 3.490, fail to reject <em>H</em><sub>0</sub>.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p341" block_type="h4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 5</strong></phrase> <strong>Calculate the Test Statistic.</strong> Calculate the between-groups sum of squares using <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-3">Equation 10.3</link>, the within-groups sum of squares using <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-4">Equation 10.4</link>, and the total sum of squares using <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-2">Equation 10.2</link>. To save time, these values have already been calculated:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p342" block_type="sr-x-eq"><em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 636.41</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p343" block_type="sr-x-eq"><em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 723.85</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p344" block_type="sr-x-eq"><em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 1,360.26</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_367" block_type="page_start">367</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p345" block_type="sr-x-txt">Use the degrees of freedom calculated in Step 4 and the sums of squares calculated in Step 4 to fill in the appropriate columns of the ANOVA summary table. Then follow the guidelines in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-30">Table 10.7</link> to complete the ANOVA summary table (<link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-58"><strong>Table 10.14</strong></link>).</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-58" block_type="table" numbered="true" number="10.14" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-58" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_table10_14.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p346" block_type="h4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="h4-n-ri"><strong>Step 6</strong></phrase> <strong>Interpret the Results.</strong> <em>Was the null hypothesis rejected?</em> To determine if the null hypothesis should be rejected, apply the decision rule. Which of these statements is true?</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-31" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p347" block_type="sr-x-bl-first">Is 3.52 &#8805; 3.490?</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p348" block_type="sr-x-bl-last">Is 3.52 &#60; 3.490?</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p349" block_type="sr-x-txt">The first statement is true, so the null hypothesis should be rejected. The results are called statistically significant, the alternative hypothesis is accepted, and it is concluded that at least one population mean differs from at least one other population mean. A post-hoc test will be needed to determine where the differences lie. For now, though, the results can be written in APA format:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p350" block_type="sr-x-eq"><em>F</em>(3, 12) &#61; 3.52, <em>p</em> &#60; .05</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p351" block_type="sr-x-txt"><em>How big is the effect?</em> This question is answered by calculating <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-27" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-59" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_367_01.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p352" block_type="sr-x-txt-ni">On the basis of Cohen&#8217;s criteria, the fact that region explains 46.79&#37; of the variability in salary means this is a very large effect.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p353" block_type="sr-x-txt"><em>Where is the effect?</em> Tukey&#8217;s <em>HSD</em> will be used as a post-hoc test to find out which pair, or pairs, of means are statistically significantly different. To calculate the <em>HSD</em> value, a researcher must know <em>q,</em> <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub>, and <em>n.</em> <em>q</em> is found in <link href="corty3e_app1_1.html#corty3e-app1-fig-18">Appendix Table 5</link> for &#945;?=?.05, in the column for <em>k</em> &#61; 4 and the row for <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 12. With <em>q</em> &#61; 4.20, <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 60.32, and <em>n</em> &#61; 4, <link href="#corty3e-ch10-bx6-9">Equation 10.9</link> is used to calculate <em>HSD:</em></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-eqn-28" block_type="equation">
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-60" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_eqn10_367_02.jpg"/></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p354" block_type="sr-x-txt-ni">Any groups that have a mean difference greater than or equal to 16.31 points are statistically significantly different. The largest mean is the Northeast at &#36;77.73 thousand and the smallest is the South at &#36;61.37 thousand. Those two are 16.36 points apart and this difference is a statistically significant difference. All other differences are smaller than 16.31 and thus not statistically significant. The effect seems to be due to the &#36;16.36 thousand difference between the mean salaries for psychologists in the Northeast and mean salaries in the South. Salaries are statistically significantly higher in the Northeast than they are in the South.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_368" block_type="page_start">368</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p355" block_type="sr-x-txt">Here is a four-point interpretation:</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p356" block_type="sr_exp_txt_v1_ni">In this study, a random sample of states from each of the four census regions was taken and the average salary in each state for clinical, counseling, and school psychologists was recorded. The mean salary in the Northeast region was &#36;77,730, &#36;63,550 in the Midwest, &#36;61,370 in the South, and &#36;68,830 in the West. The overall ANOVA showed a statistically significant effect for the region [<em>F</em>(3, 12) &#61; 3.52, <em>p</em> &#60; .05] and region accounted for almost 50&#37; of the variability in salary. However, post-hoc testing showed that the only statistically significant difference that existed was between the Northeast and the South&#8212;the mean salaries for clinical, counseling, and school psychologists are statistically higher in the Northeast than in the South. The results of this study suggest that it might be worthwhile for a psychologist living in the South to move to the North, but there would be no advantage to moving to the West or Midwest. If this study is replicated, it would be advisable to take into account the cost of living as higher salaries in a region may be mitigated by a higher cost of living.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec1-4" block_type="sum-h" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="368">
<section-metadata><section-title>SUMMARY</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p357" block_type="sum-hd1"><strong>Explain when ANOVA is used and how it works.</strong></p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-32" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p358" block_type="sum-bl-first">Analysis of variance (ANOVA) is a family of tests for comparing the means of three or more groups. Between-subjects, one-way ANOVA is used to compare the means of two or more independent samples when there is just one explanatory variable.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p359" block_type="sum-bl-first">Between-subjects, one-way ANOVA separates variability in scores into that due to the different ways the groups are treated and that due to variability between cases. If there is more variability between groups due to treatment than within groups due to individual differences, then there is a statistically significant difference among the groups.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p360" block_type="sum-hd1"><strong>Complete a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</strong></p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-33" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p361" block_type="sum-bl-first">To complete an ANOVA, the assumptions must be met and the hypotheses set. The null hypothesis says that all population means are the same and the alternative that at least one population mean differs from the others. The decision rule compares the observed <em>F</em> ratio (variability due to treatment divided by variability due to individual differences) to the critical value of <em>F .</em> Calculating an <em>F</em> ratio involves finding sums of squares and degrees of freedom for three sources of variability (between group, within group, and total) and organizing that information in an ANOVA summary table.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p362" block_type="sum-hd1"><strong>Interpret the results of a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</strong></p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-34" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p363" block_type="sum-bl-first">If the results are statistically significant, at least one population mean differs from at least one other. Then calculate the size of the effect using <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> and use post-hoc testing with the Tukey <em>HSD</em> to which pair(s) of means differ.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p364" block_type="sum-bl-first">If results are not statistically significant, then there is not enough evidence to conclude any population means are different. Nonetheless, calculate <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> in order to consider the possibility of Type II error.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e_page_369" block_type="page_start">369</p>
<box title="DIY" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx4-1" block_type="bx4-h">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p365" block_type="bx4-txt-ni">ANOVA is an extension of the <em>t</em> test, so let&#8217;s extend the DIY from the independent-samples <em>t</em> test to the between-subjects, one-way ANOVA. In that DIY, you were asked to compare two groups of states, say, northern states vs. southern states, on some outcome variable, say, murder rate. Now, divide states into three groups, say, northern, middle, and southern states, and compare them on your outcome variable.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec1-5" block_type="cr-kt-t" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="369">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<question id="corty3e-ch10-keyterms-ques1" numbered="false" title="" number="">
<query id="corty3e-ch10-keyterms-ques1-qry">MA:
a.analysis of variance (ANOVA):: a family of statistical tests for comparing the means of two or more groups.
a.between-group variability:: variability in scores that is primarily due to the different treatments that different groups receive.
a.between subjects:: ANOVA terminology for independent samples.
a.between-subjects, one-way ANOVA:: a statistical test used to compare the means of two or more independent samples when there is just one explanatory variable.
a.factor:: term for an explanatory variable in ANOVA.
a.level:: ANOVA terminology for a category of an explanatory variable.
a.post-hoc test:: a follow-up test to a statistically significant ANOVA, engineered to find out which pairs of means differ while keeping the overall alpha level at the chosen level.
a.sum of squares between (<em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>):: a sum of the squared deviation scores representing the variability between groups.
a.sum of squares total (<em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>):: a sum of the squared deviation scores representing all the variability in the scores.
a.sum of squares within (<em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>):: a sum of the squared deviation scores representing the variability within groups.
a.treatment effect:: the impact of the explanatory variable on the dependent variable.
a.way:: term for an explanatory variable in ANOVA.
a.within-group variability:: variability within a sample of cases, all of which have received the same treatment.
</query>
</question>
</section>
<section id="corty3e-ch10-sec1-6" block_type="cr-x-h" chapter="10" title="" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="369">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER EXERCISES</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p378b" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Answers to the odd-numbered exercises appear in <link href="corty3e-appb.xml">Appendix B</link>.</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p379" block_type="cr-x-hd1"><strong>Review Your Knowledge</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p380" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.01</phrase> A &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;-sample test compares the mean of one group to the mean of another group.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p381" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.02</phrase> Analysis of variance is used when comparing the means of &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; or more groups.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p382" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.03</phrase> &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; is short for analysis of variance.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p383" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.04</phrase> &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;, one-way ANOVA compares the means of two or more independent samples.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p384" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.05</phrase> Other terms used for explanatory variables in ANOVA are &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; and &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p385" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.06</phrase> The categories of an explanatory variable in ANOVA are called &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p386" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.07</phrase> ANOVA keeps the risk of &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; error at a reasonable level.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p387" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.08</phrase> The risk of making a Type I error &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; as the number of statistical tests being completed increases.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p388" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.09</phrase> A follow-up test in ANOVA is called a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; test.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p389" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.10</phrase> A &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; is used to find out which pairs of means in an ANOVA are statistically significantly different.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_370" block_type="page_start">370</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p390" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.11</phrase> ANOVA works by separating out the different sources of &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; in the scores.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p391" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.12</phrase> Variability within a set of scores is called &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; variability.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p392" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.13</phrase> Within-group variability is caused by &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p393" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.14</phrase> Making a sample more homogeneous &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; within-group variability.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p394" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.15</phrase> &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; variability is due to the different treatments different groups receive.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p395" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.16</phrase> &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; effect is the term used to label the effect of the explanatory variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p396" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.17</phrase> Between-group variability is caused by &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; as well as treatment effect.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p397" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.18</phrase> If treatment has &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; impact on outcome, the sample means are close together.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p398" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.19</phrase> When sample means are far apart, the treatment effect is &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p399" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.20</phrase> When treatment has a large impact, there is a lot of variability between group &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p400" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.21</phrase> The ratio of between-group variability to within-group variability is called an &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p401" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.22</phrase> Between-group variability, the numerator in an <em>F</em> ratio, is made up of &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; and &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p402" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.23</phrase> If treatment has no impact on outcome, the <em>F</em> ratio should be near &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p403" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.24</phrase> As treatment has an impact on outcome, the value of the <em>F</em> ratio climbs above &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p404" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.25</phrase> If there are just two groups, <em>F</em> &#61; &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; squared.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p405" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.26</phrase> Between-subjects, one-way ANOVA is used when there is one &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; and &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; groups.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p406" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.27</phrase> The assumptions for between-subjects, one-way ANOVA are the same as they are for &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p407" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.28</phrase> For a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA, the cases in each group should be &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; from the population.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p408" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.29</phrase> If the cases in the groups for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA are paired together, a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA <em>can / cannot</em> be used.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p409" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.30</phrase> Between-subjects, one-way ANOVA assumes that the dependent variable in each population is &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; distributed.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p410" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.31</phrase> The assumption that the variability in all groups is about the same is called the &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; assumption.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p411" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.32</phrase> The null hypothesis states that there is &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; mean difference between any of the populations.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p412" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.33</phrase> The null hypothesis for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA is always &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; directional.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p413" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.34</phrase> The alternative hypothesis says that at least &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; population mean is different from at least &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; other population mean.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p414" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.35</phrase> The decision rule for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA says that if <em>F</em> falls in the rare zone of the sampling distribution, the null hypothesis is &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p415" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.36</phrase> The critical value of <em>F</em> depends on the degrees of freedom for the &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; and the degrees of freedom for the &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; of the <em>F</em> value.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p416" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.37</phrase> The numerator degrees of freedom for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA <em>F</em> ratio is <em>df</em> &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p417" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.38</phrase> The denominator degrees of freedom for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA <em>F</em> ratio is <em>df</em> &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p418" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.39</phrase> In order to calculate total degrees of freedom for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA, one could add together &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; and &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p419" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.40</phrase> If <em>F</em> &#61; <em>F<sub>cv</sub>,</em> the null hypothesis is &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p420" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.41</phrase> &#8721;<em>X</em><sup>2</sup> is called a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p421" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.42</phrase> Numerators in variance formulas are &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p422" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.43</phrase> To calculate &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;, the grand mean is subtracted from each score, the difference scores are squared, and they are all added up.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p423" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.44</phrase> <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> can be broken down into two components: &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; and &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p424" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.45</phrase> <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> isolates the variability in scores that is primarily due to &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p425" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.46</phrase> <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#8722; <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_371" block_type="page_start">371</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p426" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.47</phrase> The table used to organize ANOVA results is called an &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p427" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.48</phrase> The sources of variability in an ANOVA are listed in the &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; column of an ANOVA summary table.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p428" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.49</phrase> A &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; is calculated by dividing a sum of squares by its degrees of freedom.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p429" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.50</phrase> An <em>F</em> ratio in between-subjects, one-way ANOVA is calculated as the ratio of <em>MS</em>&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; to <em>MS</em>&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p430" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.51</phrase> Interpretation of results for a statistically significant ANOVA differs from <em>t</em> in that it has to address where the &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; is located.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p431" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.52</phrase> One determines if an <em>F</em> ratio is statistically significant by comparing <em>F</em> to &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p432" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.53</phrase> If the null hypothesis is rejected, then &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; is accepted.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p433" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.54</phrase> The numbers in parentheses when reporting the results of a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA in APA format are &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; and &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p434" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.55</phrase> If the null hypothesis is not rejected, ANOVA results are reported in APA format as <em>p</em> &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; .05.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p435" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.56</phrase> &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; is used as the effect size in between-subjects, one-way ANOVA.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p436" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.57</phrase> <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> is calculated as the percentage of total variability in scores that is accounted for by &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; variability.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p437" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.58</phrase> The higher the percentage of variability in the dependent variable explained by the explanatory variable, the &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; is the size of the effect.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p438" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.59</phrase> The closer <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> is to &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#37;, the stronger the effect; the closer <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> is to &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#37;, the weaker the effect.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p439" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.60</phrase> Cohen considers an <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> of 9&#37; to be a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; effect.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p440" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.61</phrase> Post-hoc tests are only used if the ANOVA results are &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p441" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.62</phrase> Some post-hoc tests have a greater likelihood of making a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; error and others a greater chance of a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; error.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p442" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.63</phrase> The Tukey <em>HSD</em> is a conservative test. It is more likely to make a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; error than a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; error.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p443" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.64</phrase> <em>HSD</em> stands for &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p444" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.65</phrase> If the difference between two means meets or exceeds the <em>HSD</em> value, the difference is &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p445" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.66</phrase> To find a <em>q</em> value, one needs to know <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> and &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p446" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.67</phrase> The <em>n</em> in the <em>HSD</em> equation represents the sample size for the &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; group.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p447" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.68</phrase> The <em>HSD</em> test is used to determine which pairs of means have a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; difference.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p448" block_type="cr-x-hd1-rule"><strong>Apply Your Knowledge</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p449" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>For the first set of questions, select the appropriate statistical test from (a) single-sample z test; (b) single-sample t test; (c) independent-samples t test; (d) paired-samples t test; (e) between-subjects, one-way ANOVA; or (f) none of the above.</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p450" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.69</phrase> An adhesives researcher tests the holding power of a wood glue under different humidities. He glues together 100 small pieces of wood and randomly assigns each one to sit for an hour in a room with either 10&#37;, 30&#37;, 50&#37;, 70&#37;, or 90&#37; relative humidity. Each glued piece of wood is then tested to see how many pounds of weight it takes to break the glue bond. The means of the five groups are compared.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p451" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.70</phrase> Some parents demand that their children friend them on Facebook and other parents don&#8217;t. A developmental psychologist wondered if such parental supervision had any impact on behavior. She obtained a sample of first-year college students and classified them as having parents who were or were not Facebook friends. From each student she also learned the number of days, during the first month of college, that he or she had consumed any alcohol. The two means are compared.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p452" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.71</phrase> A nutritionist investigates the impact of type of breakfast on mid-morning concentration. He puts together a sample of 50 adults. He feeds them a breakfast and 4 hours later measures their concentration on an interval-level concentration test. On one day he feeds them bacon and eggs, on a second day he feeds them oatmeal, and on a third day he has them skip breakfast. He then calculates the mean concentration score for each condition.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_372" block_type="page_start">372</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p453" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.72</phrase> A social psychologist is interested in how people perceive age-discrepant couples. She gets a random sample of shoppers at a mall, has them read a wedding announcement, and then asks them to predict&#8212;on an interval-level scale&#8212;the newlyweds&#8217; degree of marital happiness after 10 years of marriage. Participants are randomly assigned to groups: one-third read an announcement in which the bride is 25 and the groom 35, one-third read an announcement in which the bride is 35 and the groom 25, and the final third read an announcement in which both bride and groom are 30.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p454" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>For the next set of questions, determine if assumptions have been violated and if a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA can be completed.</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p455" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.73</phrase> A sensory psychologist wants to determine if a sensory threshold differs depending on which nostril is used. He obtains 30 introductory psychology student volunteers and measures the absolute threshold, in parts per million, for detecting the scent of peppermint. Participants are randomly assigned to three equal-size groups: (1) scent administered to the left nostril, (2) scent administered to the right nostril, and (3) scent administered to both nostrils. Each participant is tested individually by an experimenter who does not know what the hypothesis is and does not know which nostril is being used.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p456" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.74</phrase> A biomedical engineer compared the abrasion resistance &#8212; as measured by number of rotations until failure &#8212; of three different artificial hips. Manufacturer X makes hip joints out of metal, manufacturer Y out of ceramic, and manufacturer Z out of a metal/ceramic composite. The biomedical engineer gets a random sample of 6 hips from each manufacturer&#8217;s production line and tests each one individually until failure occurs.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p457" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Writing the hypotheses</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p458" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.75</phrase> Write the null and alternative hypotheses for the between-subjects, one-way ANOVA in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-p455">Exercise 10.73</link>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p459" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.76</phrase> Write the null and alternative hypotheses for the between-subjects, one-way ANOVA in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-p456">Exercise 10.74</link>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p460" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Calculating degrees of freedom</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p461" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.77</phrase> If <em>N</em> &#61; 48 and <em>k</em> &#61; 4, calculate (a) <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub>, (b) <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub>, and (c) <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p462" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.78</phrase> If <em>N</em> &#61; 120 and <em>k</em> &#61; 5, calculate (a) <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub>, (b <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub>, and (c) <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p463" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.79</phrase> If there are four independent samples, each with 15 participants, what are (a) <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub>, (b) <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub>, and (c) <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p464" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.80</phrase> If <em>n</em><sub>1</sub> &#61; 15, <em>n</em><sub>2</sub> &#61; 12, and <em>n</em><sub>3</sub> &#61; 18, what are (a) <em>df</em><sub>Total</sub>, (b) <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub>, and (c) <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p465" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Finding F<sub>cv</sub></em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p466" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.81</phrase> If <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 44 and <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 2, what is <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> if &#945; &#61; .01?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p467" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.82</phrase> If <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 3 and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 36, what is <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> if &#945;= .05?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p468" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.83</phrase> If &#945; &#61; .05, <em>N</em> &#61; 50, and <em>k</em> &#61; 4, what is <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p469" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.84</phrase> If &#945; &#61; .05, <em>N</em> &#61; 80, and <em>k</em> &#61; 5, what is <em>F</em><sub>cv</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p470" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Stating the decision rule</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p471" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.85</phrase> If <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 40 and <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 2, what is the decision rule if &#945; &#61; .05? Draw a sampling distribution of <em>F</em> and mark the rare and common zones.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p472" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.86</phrase> If <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 10 and <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 3, what is the decision rule if &#945; &#61; .05? Draw a sampling distribution of <em>F</em> and mark the rare and common zones.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p473" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Calculating sums of squares</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p474" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.87</phrase> Prepare the data table for use by computational formulas for sums of squares.</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table4" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 1</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 2</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 3</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">108</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">100</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">99</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">102</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">105</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">95</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">91</phrase></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p475" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.88</phrase> Prepare the data table for use by computational formulas for sums of squares.</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table5" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 1</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 2</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 3</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">46</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">54</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">74</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">48</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">58</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">80</phrase></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e_page_373" block_type="page_start">373</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p476" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.89</phrase> Given the data in this table, calculate <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>, and <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>.</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table6" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-blue-bg">
<td></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 1</strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 2</strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 3</strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-blue-bg">
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">112</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">12,544</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">98</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">9,604</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">88</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">7,744</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">104</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">10,816</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">90</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">8,100</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">85</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">7,225</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">88</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">7,744</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">76</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">5,776</phrase></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-blue-bg"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Grand</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">80</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td class="tbl-blue-bg"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td class="tbl-blue-bg"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-SIDHD"><strong>&#8721;</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">216.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">23,360.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">276.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">25,448.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">329.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">27,145.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">821.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">75,953.00</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-SIDHD"><strong>n</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">9</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p477" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.90</phrase> Given the data in this table, calculate <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>, and <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>.</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table7" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-blue-bg">
<td></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 1</strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 2</strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Group 3</strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-blue-bg">
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">55</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3,025</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">47</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2,209</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">68</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4,624</phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">63</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3,969</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">58</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3,364</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">66</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4,356</phrase></td>
<td colspan="2"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">72</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">5,184</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">63</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3,969</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">62</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3,844</phrase></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-blue-bg"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Grand</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">59</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3,481</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">48</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2,304</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">73</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">5,329</phrase></td>
<td class="tbl-blue-bg"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em></strong></phrase></td>
<td class="tbl-blue-bg"><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>X</em><sup>2</sup></strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-SIDHD"><strong>&#8721;</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">249</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">15,659</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">216</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">11,846</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">269</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">18,153</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">734</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">45,658</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-SIDHD"><strong>n</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">12</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p478" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.91</phrase> If <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 98.75 and <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 40.33, what is <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p479" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.92</phrase> If <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 168.43 and <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 764.13, what is <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p480" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Calculating mean squares</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p481" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.93</phrase> If <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 2,378.99 and <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 3, what is <em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p482" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.94</phrase> If <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 138.76 and <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 4, what is <em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p483" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.95</phrase> If <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 78.95 and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 32, what is <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p484" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.96</phrase> If <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 452.86 and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 102, what is <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p485" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Calculating F</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p486" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.97</phrase> If <em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 38.88 and <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 17.44, what is <em>F</em>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p487" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.98</phrase> If <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 764.55 and <em>MS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 898.00, what is <em>F</em>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p488" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Completing an ANOVA summary table</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p489" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.99</phrase> Complete this ANOVA summary table:</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table8" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Source of Variability</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Sum of Squares</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Degrees of Freedom</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Mean Square</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>F</em> ratio</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Between groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">172.80</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Within groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">6,410.80</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">12</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Total</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">6,583.60</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">14</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p490" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.100</phrase> Complete this ANOVA summary table:</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table9" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Source of Variability</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Sum of Squares</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Degrees of Freedom</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Mean Square</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>F</em> ratio</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Between groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">47,843.15</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Within groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3,053.88</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">30</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Total</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">50,897.03</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">33</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e_page_374" block_type="page_start">374</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p491" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Deciding if the null hypothesis is rejected</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p492" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.101</phrase> If <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> &#61; 3.238, draw a sampling distribution of <em>F,</em> label the rare and common zones, locate <em>F</em> &#61; 1.96, and determine, for this <em>F</em> value, if the null hypothesis should be rejected.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p493" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.102</phrase> If <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> &#61; 2.337, draw a sampling distribution of <em>F,</em> label the rare and common zones, locate <em>F</em> &#61; 5.66, and determine, for this <em>F</em> value, if the null hypothesis should be rejected.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p494" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.103</phrase> If <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> &#61; 3.467 and <em>F</em> &#61; 7.64, is the null hypothesis rejected?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p495" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.104</phrase> If <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> &#61; 2.486 and <em>F</em> &#61; 1.98, is the null hypothesis rejected?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p496" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Using APA format</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p497" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.105</phrase> If <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 3, <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 17, <em>F</em> &#61; 5.34, and &#945; &#61; .05, write the results in APA format. (Use <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> to find <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> in order to determine if the null hypothesis was rejected.)</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p498" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.106</phrase> If <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 6, <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 30, <em>F</em> &#61; 2.81, and &#945; &#61; .05, write the results in APA format. (Use <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> to find <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> in order to determine if the null hypothesis was rejected.)</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p499" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.107</phrase> Given this ANOVA summary table, write the results in APA format using &#945; &#61; .05. (Use <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> to find <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> in order to determine if the null hypothesis was rejected.)</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table10" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Source of Variability</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Sum of Squares</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Degrees of Freedom</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Mean Square</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>F</em> ratio</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Between groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">59.98</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">19.99</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">3.28</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Within groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">268.60</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">44</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">6.10</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Total</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">328.58</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">47</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p500" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.108</phrase> Given this ANOVA summary table, write the results in APA format using &#945; &#61; .05. (Use <em>df</em><sub>Between</sub> and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> to find <em>F<sub>cv</sub></em> in order to determine if the null hypothesis was rejected.)</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table11" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Source of Variability</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Sum of Squares</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Degrees of Freedom</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Mean Square</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>F</em> ratio</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Between groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">42.34</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">21.17</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2.23</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Within groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">1,896.22</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">200</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">9.48</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Total</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">1,938.56</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">202</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p501" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Interpreting APA format</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p502" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.109</phrase> The results of a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA, in APA format, are <em>F</em>(3, 26) &#61; 4.53, <em>p</em> &#60; .05. What interpretative statement can one make about the differences among the four population means?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p503" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.110</phrase> The results of a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA, in APA format, are <em>F</em>(3, 30) &#61; 2.66, <em>p</em> > .05. What interpretative statement can one make about the differences among the four population means?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p504" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Calculating r<sup>2</sup></em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p505" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.111</phrase> If <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 128.86 and <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 413.67, what is <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p506" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.112</phrase> f <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 17.48 and <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 342.88, what is <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p507" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.113</phrase> Using the information in the ANOVA summary table in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-p499">Exercise 10.107</link>, calculate <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p508" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.114</phrase> Using the information in the ANOVA summary table in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-p500">Exercise 10.108</link>, calculate <em>r</em><sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p509" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Deciding whether to do a post-hoc test</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p510" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.115</phrase> Should a post-hoc test be completed for the results in the ANOVA summary table in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-p499">Exercise 10.107</link>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p511" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.116</phrase> Should a post-hoc test be completed for the results in the ANOVA summary table in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-p500">Exercise 10.108</link>?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p512" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Finding q</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p513" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.117</phrase> If <em>k</em> &#61; 4 and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 16, what is <em>q</em> if &#945;?= .01?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p514" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.118</phrase> If <em>k</em> &#61; 3 and <em>df</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 26, what is <em>q</em> if &#945;?= .05?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p515" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Calculating HSD</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p516" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.119</phrase> If <em>q</em> &#61; 3.55, <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 10.44, and <em>n</em> &#61; 8, what is <em>HSD</em> ?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p517" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.120</phrase> If <em>q</em> &#61; 4.05, <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 6.87, and <em>n</em> &#61; 11, what is <em>HSD</em> ?</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_375" block_type="page_start">375</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p518" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Interpreting HSD</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p519" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.121</phrase> If <em>M</em><sub>1</sub> &#61; 13.09, <em>M</em><sub>2</sub> &#61; 8.89, and <em>HSD</em> &#61; 4.37, is the difference a statistically significant one? What conclusion would one draw about the direction of the difference between the two population means?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p520" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.122</phrase> If <em>M</em><sub>1</sub> &#61; 123.65, <em>M</em><sub>2</sub> &#61; 144.56, and <em>HSD</em> &#61; 10.64, is the difference a statistically significant one? What conclusion would one draw about the direction of the difference between the two population means?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p521" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.123</phrase> If <em>M</em><sub>1</sub> &#61; 67.86, <em>M</em><sub>2</sub> &#61; 53.56, <em>M</em><sub>3</sub> = 61.55, and <em>HSD</em> &#61; 8.30, which pairs of means have statistically significant differences? What is the direction of the differences?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p522" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.124</phrase> If <em>M</em><sub>1</sub> &#61; 12.55, <em>M</em><sub>2</sub> &#61; 13.74, <em>M</em><sub>3</sub> &#61; 5.49, and <em>HSD</em> &#61; 4.44, which pairs of means have statistically significant differences? What is the direction of the differences?</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p523" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>Completing an interpretation (HSD values are given whether needed or not).</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p524" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.125</phrase> An addictions researcher was curious about which drug was hardest to quit: alcohol, cigarettes, or heroin. She obtained samples of alcoholics, smokers, and heroin addicts who were in treatment for the second time and found out how long they had remained abstinent, in months, after their first treatment. The mean time to relapse for the 8 alcoholics was 4.63 months; for the 11 smokers, it was 4.91 months; for the 6 heroin addicts, it was 5.17 months. Given the ANOVA summary table below, <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> &#61; 0.66&#37;, and <em>HSD</em> &#61; 3.83, complete a four-point interpretation of the results using &#945; &#61; .05.</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table12" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Source of Variability</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Sum of Squares</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Degrees of Freedom</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Mean Square</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>F</em> ratio</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Between groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">1.02</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">0.51</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">0.07</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Within groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">153.62</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">22</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">6.98</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Total</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">154.64</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">24</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p525" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.126</phrase> A sleep specialist investigated the impact of watching TV and using computers, before bedtime, on sleep onset. He obtained 30 college student volunteers and randomly assigned them to three equally sized groups: (1) work on a computer for 30 minutes before going to bed, (2) watch TV for 30 minutes before going to bed, and (3) don&#8217;t work on a computer or watch TV before bedtime. He then measured time to sleep onset (in minutes), finding means for the three groups, respectively, of 19.60, 17.40, and 5.30. Given the ANOVA summary table, <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> &#61; 65.63&#37;, and <em>HSD</em> &#61; 5.32, complete a four-point interpretation of the results using &#945; &#61; .05.</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table13" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Source of Variability</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Sum of Squares</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Degrees of Freedom</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Mean Square</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong><em>F</em> ratio</strong></phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Between groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">1,185.80</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">2</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">592.90</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">25.78</phrase></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Within groups</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">620.90</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">27</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">23.00</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><strong>Total</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">1,806.70</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">29</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p526" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>For Exercises 10.127&#8211;10.128, complete all six steps of hypothesis testing for these data sets. Remember to keep the six steps in the right order.</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p527" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.127</phrase> A consumer researcher gave consumers a sample shampoo. After using the shampoo, each consumer used an interval-level scale to rate his or her satisfaction with it. Scores could range from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating greater satisfaction. Consumers didn&#8217;t know each other and were randomly assigned to three groups: (1) receive a store brand of shampoo in a bottle clearly labeled as such, (2) receive a premium brand of shampoo in the premium brand&#8217;s bottle, or (3) receive a store brand of shampoo in the premium brand&#8217;s bottle. Here are the collected data:</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table14" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Store Brand, Store Bottle</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Premium Brand, Premium Bottle</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Store Brand, Premium Bottle</strong></phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">70</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">85</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">85</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">65</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">90</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">80</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">65</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">95</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">90</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">60</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">90</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">85</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><em>M</em> &#61; 65.00 <em>s</em> &#61; 4.08</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><em>M</em> &#61; 90.00 <em>s</em> &#61; 4.08</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><em>M</em> &#61; 85.00 <em>s</em> &#61; 4.08</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><em>M</em><sub>Grand</sub> &#61; 80.00</phrase></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e_page_376" block_type="page_start">376</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p528" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.128</phrase> An environmental psychologist investigated ways to reduce waste. He randomly assigned office workers in small businesses to three groups: (1) to be in a control group, (2) to receive daily e-mail reminders about the importance of recycling, or (3) to have their current wastebaskets replaced with much smaller wastebaskets. To make sure they didn&#8217;t influence each other, each worker was selected from a different small business. At the end of the week, the psychologist measured how many pounds of office waste each person had generated. Here are the data:</p>
<table id="corty3e-ch10-table15" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Control Group</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Daily e-mail Reminders</strong></phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="TBN-COLHD"><strong>Smaller Wastebaskets</strong></phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">12</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">14</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">6</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">14</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">12</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">4</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">18</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">10</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">8</phrase></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt">12</phrase></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><em>M</em> &#61; 14.00 <em>s</em> &#61; 2.83</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><em>M</em> &#61; 12.00 <em>s</em> &#61; 2.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><em>M</em> &#61; 6.00 <em>s</em> &#61; 2.00</phrase></td>
<td><phrase block_type="tbn-txt"><em>M</em><sub>Grand</sub> &#61; 11.00</phrase></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p529" block_type="cr-x-hd1"><strong>Expand Your Knowledge</strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p530" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.129</phrase> Which of the following is in descending order of size?</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-35" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p531" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc"><em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub></p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p532" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc"><em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub></p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p533" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc"><em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>, <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub></p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p534" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc"><em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>, <em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub></p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p535" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc"><em>MS</em><sub>Within</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>, <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub></p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p536" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc">None of the above.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p537" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.130</phrase> If treatment has an effect, then there is:</p>
<list id="corty3e-ch10-list-36" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p538" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc">more variability between groups than in total.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p539" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc">more variability within groups than in total.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p540" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc">more variability between groups than within groups.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p541" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc">more variability within groups than between groups.</p></li>
<li><p id="corty3e-ch10-p542" block_type="cr-x-nl-alpha-lc">None of the above.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p543" block_type="cr-x-txt-ni"><strong><em>For Exercises 10.131&#8211;10.138, indicate whether what is written could be true or is false.</em></strong></p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p544" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.131</phrase> <em>F</em>(3, 18) &#61; 10.98, <em>p</em> &#60; .05</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p545" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.132</phrase> <em>F</em>(3, 25) &#61; 1.98, <em>p</em> &#60; .05</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p546" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.133</phrase> <em>F</em>(4, 20) &#61; &#8722;17.89, <em>p</em> &#60; .05</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p547" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.134</phrase> <em>N</em> &#61; 14, <em>k</em> &#61; 3</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p548" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.135</phrase> <em>N</em> &#61; 6, <em>k</em> &#61; 8</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p549" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.136</phrase> If &#945; = .05, <em>q</em> &#61; 1.96.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p550" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.137</phrase> <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 25, <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 10, <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 35</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p551" block_type="cr-x-nl-txt"><phrase block_type="question_num">10.138</phrase> <em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub> &#61; 12.50, <em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub> &#61; 12.50, <em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub> &#61; 25.00</p>
<box title="SPSS" numbered="false" id="corty3e-ch10-bx3-4" block_type="bx3-h">
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p552" block_type="bx3-txt-ni">The data for a between-subjects, one-way ANOVA have to be entered in the SPSS data editor in a specific way. <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-61"><strong>Figure 10.16</strong></link> contains the data for psychologists&#8217; salaries for states in the four census regions. The first column in the data editor tells which state the data come from. The second variable, the column labeled &#8220;region,&#8221; contains information about which group a case is in. Here, a 1 indicates that a case is in the Northeast, a 2 indicates the Midwest, a 3 is for cases in the South, and a 4 is for the West. Note that SPSS does not need cases in a region to be grouped together. The final variable, the column labeled &#8220;psych,&#8221; contains the cases&#8217; scores on the dependent variable, the mean salary for the state.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-61" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.16" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-61" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_16.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.16</phrase> Data Entry in SPSS for a One-Way ANOVA</strong> At least two columns are needed to enter data for a one-way ANOVA in SPSS (just as for the independent-samples <em>t</em> test). One column, &#8220;region,&#8221; contains information about which group a case belongs to and another column, &#8220;psych,&#8221; has the case&#8217;s score on the dependent variable.</caption>
<asset_source>(Source: SPSS)</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p553" block_type="bx3-txt">The command to start a one-way ANOVA can be found under &#8220;Analyze&#8221; and &#8220;Compare Means,&#8221; as shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-62"><strong>Figure 10.17</strong></link>.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-62" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.17" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-62" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_17.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.17</phrase> Starting a One-Way ANOVA in SPSS</strong> The command &#8220;One-Way ANOVA. . .&#8221; is found under the &#8220;Compare Means&#8221; heading under &#8220;Analyze.&#8221;</caption>
<asset_source>(Source: SPSS)</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p554" block_type="bx3-txt">Clicking on &#8220;One-Way ANOVA. . .&#8221; opens up the commands shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-63"><strong>Figure 10.18</strong></link>. &#8220;psych,&#8221; the dependent variable, has already been moved over to the box labeled &#8220;Dependent List.&#8221; &#8220;region,&#8221; the explanatory variable, is moved over to the box labeled &#8220;Factor.&#8221;</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-63" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.18" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-63" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_18.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.18</phrase> Defining the Dependent Variable and Explanatory Variable for a One-Way ANOVA in SPSS</strong> Once the dependent variable (psych) has been moved to &#8220;Dependent List:&#8221; and the explanatory variable (region) to &#8220;Factor:&#8221;, clicking on the &#8220;OK&#8221; button will start the analysis of variance.</caption>
<asset_source>(Source: SPSS)</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_377" block_type="page_start">377</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_378" block_type="page_start">378</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p555" block_type="bx3-txt">Clicking on &#8220;OK&#8221; produces the output shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-64"><strong>Figure 10.19</strong></link>. Note that SPSS produces an ANOVA summary table like the one in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-55">Table 10.14</link>. The SPSS summary table has an extra column on the right, labeled &#8220;Sig.&#8221; This column reports the exact significance level for the <em>F</em> ratio. If the value reported in the &#8220;Sig.&#8221; column is less than or equal to .05, then the results are statistically significant and the results are written in APA format as <em>p</em> &#60; .05. If the &#8220;Sig.&#8221; level is greater than .05, then one has failed to reject the null hypothesis and the results are written in APA format as <em>p</em> &#62; .05.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-64" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.19" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-64" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_19.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.19</phrase> Example of One-Way ANOVA Output from SPSS</strong> SPSS produces an ANOVA summary table. The column labeled &#8220;Sig.&#8221; provides the exact significance level for the <em>F</em> ratio. If the &#8220;Sig.&#8221; value is &#8804;.05, the results are written as <em>p</em> &#60; .05 in APA format. If the &#8220;Sig.&#8221; value is &#62;.05, write the results as <em>p</em> &#62; .05.</caption>
<asset_source>(Source: SPSS)</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p556" block_type="bx3-txt">Here, the exact significance level is .049, which is less than .05, so the null hypothesis is rejected. If the exact significance level is known, as it is here, then it should be reported in APA format. These results would be reported as <em>F</em>(3, 12) &#61; 3.52, p &#61; .049.</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p557" block_type="bx3-txt">Once a researcher knows that the <em>F</em> ratio was statistically significant, he or she can proceed to select a post-hoc test by clicking the &#8220;Post Hoc&#8221; button seen in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-62">Figure 10.17</link>. This opens up the selection of post-hoc tests seen in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-65"><strong>Figure 10.20</strong></link>. &#8220;Tukey,&#8221; which is the Tukey <em>HSD</em> test covered in this chapter, has been selected. If a researcher wants to change the significance level from .05, now is the time to do so.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-65" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.20" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-65" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_20.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.20</phrase> Choosing a Post-Hoc Test in SPSS</strong> This is the dialog box that opens up when one clicks on &#8220;Post Hoc&#8221; in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-63">Figure 10.18</link>. Note the wide variety of post-hoc tests that are available. &#8220;Tukey,&#8221; which is Tukey&#8217;s <em>HSD,</em> has been selected.</caption>
<asset_source>(Source: SPSS)</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="corty3e_page_379" block_type="page_start">379</p>
<p id="corty3e-ch10-p558" block_type="bx3-txt">The output from the <em>HSD</em> test is shown in <link href="#corty3e-ch10-fig-66"><strong>Figure 10.21</strong></link>. SPSS is redundant and has 12 rows in the table when it only needs 6. The first row, for example, compares the Northeast region to the Midwest region, and the fourth row turns this around to compare the Midwest region to the Northeast region. It is exactly the same comparison, though one finds a mean difference of 14.17750 and the other &#8722;14.17750. SPSS doesn&#8217;t report the <em>HSD</em> values, but it does report each mean difference that is statistically significant at the .05 level. It does this, as mentioned in the table footnote, by placing an asterisk after each mean difference that is statistically significant.</p>
<figure id="corty3e-ch10-fig-66" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="10.21" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="corty3e-ch10-img-66" alt="image" src="asset/ch10/corty3e_fig10_21.jpg"/>
<caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_num">Figure 10.21</phrase> Output for Post-Hoc Tests in SPSS</strong> Each row in this table compares a pair of means. SPSS is redundant and compares each pair of means twice. For example, the first row (Northeast vs. Midwest) is the same as the fourth row (Midwest vs. Northeast). All that changes is the direction of the mean difference. Also, note the footnote on the table&#8212;asterisks that follow the mean difference indicate the difference is a statistically significant one. The exact significance level is found in the column labeled &#8220;Sig.&#8221;</caption>
<asset_source>(Source: SPSS)</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="corty3e_page_380" block_type="page_start">380</p>
</section>
</chapter>
