<chapter number="1" id="corty3e-glossary" title="Glossary" start-numbering-at="01" numbered="true">
<section id="corty3e-gls1-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Glossary" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="G-1">
<p id="corty3e_page_G-1" block_type="page_start">G-1</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p2" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>alpha (or alpha level)</strong> &#8211; the probability of making a Type I error; the probability that a result will fall in the rare zone and the null hypothesis will be rejected when the null hypothesis is true; often called significance level; abbreviated &#945;; usually set at .05 or 5&#37;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p3" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>alternative hypothesis</strong> &#8211; abbreviated <em>H</em><sub>1</sub>; a statement that the explanatory variable has an effect on the outcome variable in the population; usually, a statement of what the researcher believes to be true.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p4" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>analysis of variance (ANOVA)</strong> &#8211; a family of statistical tests for comparing the means of two or more groups.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p5" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>apparent limits</strong> &#8211; what seem to be the upper and lower bounds of an interval in a grouped frequency distribution.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p6" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>bar graph</strong> &#8211; a graph of a frequency distribution for discrete data that uses the heights of bars to indicate frequency; the bars do not touch.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p7" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>beta</strong> &#8211; the probability of making a Type II error; abbreviated &#946;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p8" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>between-group variability</strong> &#8211; variability in scores that is primarily due to the different treatments that different groups receive.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p9" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>between-subjects</strong> &#8211; ANOVA terminology for independent samples.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p10" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>between-subjects, one-way ANOVA</strong> &#8211; a statistical test used to compare the means of two or more independent samples when there is just one explanatory variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p11" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>cases</strong> &#8211; the participants in or subjects of a study.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p12" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>central limit theorem</strong> &#8211; a statement about the shape that a sampling distribution of the mean takes if the size of the samples is large and every possible sample were obtained.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p13" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>central tendency</strong> &#8211; a value used to summarize a set of scores; also known as the average.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p14" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>chi-square goodness-of-fit test</strong> &#8211; a nonparametric, single-sample test used to compare the distribution of a categorical (nominal- or ordinal-level) outcome variable in a sample to a known population value.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p15" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>chi-square test of independence</strong> &#8211; a nonparametric test used to determine whether two or more populations of cases differ on a categorical (nominal- or ordinal-level) outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p16" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>clinical significance (or practical significance)</strong> &#8211; whether the size of the effect is large enough to say the explanatory variable has a meaningful impact on clinical outcome.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p17" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>coefficient of determination</strong> &#8722; formal name for the effect size <em>r</em> <sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p18" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>Cohen&#8217;s <em>d</em></strong> &#8211; a standardized measure of effect used to measure the difference between means.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p19" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>common zone</strong> &#8211; the section of the sampling distribution of a test statistic in which the observed outcome should fall if the null hypothesis is true; typically set to be the middle 95&#37;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p20" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>confidence interval</strong> &#8211; a range within which it is estimated, based on a sample value, that a population value falls.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p21" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>confounding variable</strong> &#8211; a third variable in correlational and quasi-experimental designs that is not controlled for and that has an impact on <em>both</em> of the other variables.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p22" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>consent rate</strong> &#8211; the percentage of targeted subjects who agree to participate in a study.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p23" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>contingency table</strong> &#8211; a table showing the degree to which a case&#8217;s value on the outcome variable depends on its category on the explanatory variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p24" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>continuous number</strong> &#8211; number that answers the question &#8220;how much&#8221; and can have &#8220;in-between&#8221; values; the specificity of the number, the number of decimal places reported, depends on the precision of the measuring instrument.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p25" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>convenience sample</strong> &#8211; a sampling strategy in which cases are selected for study based on the ease with which they can be obtained.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p26" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>correlation coefficient</strong> &#8722; a statistic that summarizes, in a single number, the strength of a relationship between two variables.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_G-2" block_type="page_start">G-2</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p27" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>correlational design</strong> &#8211; a scientific study in which the relationship between two variables is examined without any attempt to manipulate or control them.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p28" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>criterion variable</strong> &#8211; the outcome variable in a correlational design.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p29" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>critical value</strong> &#8211; the value of the test statistic that forms the boundary between the rare zone and the common zone of the sampling distribution of the test statistic.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p30" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>critical value of <em>t</em></strong> &#8211; value of <em>t</em> used to determine whether a null hypothesis is rejected or not; abbreviated <em>t<sub>cv</sub></em>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p31" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>crossed</strong> &#8211; a factorial ANOVA in which each level of each explanatory variable occurs with each level of the other explanatory variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p32" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>cumulative frequency</strong> &#8211; a count of how often a given value, or a lower value, occurs in a set of data.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p33" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>cumulative percentage</strong> &#8211; cumulative frequency expressed as a percentage of the number of cases in the data set.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p34" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>degrees of freedom (<em>df</em>)</strong> &#8211; the number of values in a sample that are free to vary.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p35" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>dependent samples</strong> &#8211; samples in which the selection of cases for one group is related to, influences, or is determined by case selection for another group.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p36" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>dependent variable</strong> &#8211; the variable where the effect is measured in an experimental or quasi-experimental study; an outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p37" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>descriptive statistic</strong> &#8211; a summary statement about a set of cases.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p38" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>descriptive statistics</strong> &#8211; statistics used to describe a set of observations.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p39" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>deviation score</strong> &#8211; a measure of how far away a score falls from the mean.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p40" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>difference tests</strong> &#8211; statistical tests that look for differences among groups of cases.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p41" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>direct relationship</strong> &#8722; a relationship in which high scores on <em>X</em> are associated with high scores on <em>Y</em>. Also called a positive relationship.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p42" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>discrete number</strong> &#8211; numbers that answer the question &#8220;how many,&#8221; take whole number values, and have no &#8220;in-between&#8221; values.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p43" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>effect size</strong> &#8211; a measure of the degree of impact of the explanatory variable on the outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p44" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>eta squared (&#951;<sup>2</sup>)</strong> &#8211; an effect size that calculates the percentage of variability in the outcome variable accounted for by the explanatory variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p45" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>experimental design</strong> &#8211; a scientific study in which an explanatory variable is manipulated or controlled by the experimenter and the effect that is measured in a dependent variable allows for a cause and effect conclusion.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p46" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>explanatory variable</strong> &#8211; the variable that causes, predicts, or explains the outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p47" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>extreme percentage</strong> &#8211; percentage of the normal distribution that is found in the two tails and is evenly divided between them.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p48" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>factor</strong> &#8211; term for an explanatory variable in ANOVA.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p49" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>factorial ANOVA</strong> &#8211; an analysis of variance in which there is more than one explanatory variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p50" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>frequency distribution</strong> &#8211; a tally of how often different values of a variable occur in a set of data.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p51" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>frequency polygon</strong> &#8211; a frequency distribution for continuous data, displayed in graphical format, using a line connecting dots above interval midpoints to indicate frequency.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p52" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>grouped frequency distribution</strong> &#8211; a count of how often the values of a variable, grouped into intervals, occur in a set of data.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p53" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>grouping variable</strong> &#8211; the variable that is the explanatory variable in a quasi-experimental design.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p54" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>histogram</strong> &#8211; a frequency distribution for continuous data, displayed in graph form, using the heights of bars to indicate frequency; the bars touch each other.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p55" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>hypothesis</strong> &#8211; a proposed explanation for observed facts; a statement or prediction about a population value.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p56" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>hypothesis testing</strong> &#8211; a statistical procedure in which data from a sample are used to evaluate a hypothesis about a population.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p57" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>independence</strong> &#8211; in probability, when the occurrence of one outcome does not have any impact on the occurrence of a second outcome.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p58" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>independent samples</strong> &#8211; when the selection of cases for one sample has no impact on the selection of cases for another sample.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p59" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>independent-samples <em>t</em> test</strong> &#8211; an inferential statistical test used to compare two independent samples on an interval- or ratio-level outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p60" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>independent variable</strong> &#8211; the variable that is controlled by the experimenter in an experimental design.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p61" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>individual differences</strong> &#8211; attributes that vary from case to case.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p62" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>inferential statistic</strong> &#8211; using observations from a sample to draw a conclusion about a population.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p63" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>interaction effect</strong> &#8211; situation, in factorial ANOVA, in which the impact of one explanatory variable on the outcome variable depends on the level of another explanatory variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_G-3" block_type="page_start">G-3</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p64" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>interquartile range</strong> &#8211; a measure of variability for interval- or ratio-level data; the distance covered by the middle 50&#37; of scores; abbreviated <em>IQR</em>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p65" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>interval estimate</strong> &#8211; an estimate of a population value that says the population value falls somewhere within a range of values.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p66" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>interval-level numbers</strong> &#8211; numbers that provide information about how much of an attribute is possessed, as well as information about same/different and more/less; interval-level numbers have equality of units and an arbitrary zero point.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p67" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>inverse relationship</strong> &#8722; a relationship in which high scores on <em>X</em> are associated with low scores on <em>Y</em>. Also called a negative relationship.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p68" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>kurtosis</strong> &#8211; how peaked or flat a frequency distribution is.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p69" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>least squares criterion</strong> &#8211; prediction errors are squared and the best-fitting regression line is the one that has the smallest sum of squared errors.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p70" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>level</strong> &#8211; ANOVA terminology for a category of an explanatory variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p71" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>linear regression</strong> &#8211; a predictor variable is used to predict a case&#8217;s score on another variable and the prediction equation takes the form of a straight line.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p72" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>longitudinal research (or repeated-measures design)</strong> &#8211; a study in which the same participants are measured at two or more points in time.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p73" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>main effect</strong> &#8211; the impact of an explanatory variable, by itself, on the outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p74" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>Mann&#8211;Whitney <em>U</em> test</strong> &#8211; a nonparametric test used to compare two independent samples on an ordinal-level outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p75" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>matched pairs</strong> &#8211; participants are grouped into sets of two based on their being similar on potential confounding variables.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p76" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>mean</strong> &#8211; an average calculated for interval- or ratio-level data by summing all the values in a data set and dividing by the number of cases; abbreviated <em>M</em>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p77" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>median</strong> &#8211; an average calculated by finding the score associated with the middle case, the case that separates the top half of scores from the bottom half; abbreviated <em>Mdn;</em> can be calculated for ordinal-, interval-, or ratio-level data.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p78" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>middle percentage</strong> &#8211; percentage of the normal distribution found around the midpoint, evenly divided into two parts, one just above the mean and one just below it.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p79" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>midpoint</strong> &#8211; the middle of an interval in a grouped frequency distribution.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p80" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>modality</strong> &#8211; the number of peaks that exist in a frequency distribution.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p81" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>mode</strong> &#8211; the score that occurs with the greatest frequency.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p82" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>multiple linear regression</strong> &#8211; prediction in which multiple predictor variables are combined to predict an outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p83" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>negative relationship</strong> &#8722; a relationship in which high scores on <em>X</em> are associated with low scores on <em>Y;</em> also called an inverse relationship.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p84" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>negative skew</strong> &#8211; an asymmetrical frequency distribution in which the tail extends to the left, in the direction of lower scores.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p85" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>nominal-level numbers</strong> &#8211; numbers used to place cases in categories; numbers are arbitrary and only provide information about same/different.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p86" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>nonparametric test</strong> &#8211; a statistical test for use with nominal- or ordinal-level outcome variables, and for which assumptions about the shape of the population don&#8217;t have to be met.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p87" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>nonrobust assumption</strong> &#8211; an assumption for a statistical test that must be met in order to proceed with the test.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p88" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>normal distribution</strong> &#8211; also called the normal curve; a specific bell-shaped curve defined by the percentage of cases that fall in specific areas under the curve.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p89" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>null hypothesis</strong> &#8211; abbreviated <em>H</em><sub>0</sub>; a statement that in the population the explanatory variable has no impact on the outcome variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p90" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>one-tailed hypothesis test</strong> &#8211; hypothesis that predicts the explanatory variable has an impact on the outcome variable in a specific direction.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p91" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>ordinal-level numbers</strong> &#8211; numbers used to indicate if more or less of an attribute is possessed; numbers provide information about same/different and more/less.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p92" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>outcome variable</strong> &#8722; the variable that is caused, predicted, or influenced by the explanatory variable; the variable in a relationship test, <em>Y</em>, that is predicted from the other variable, <em>X</em>. Sometimes called the dependent variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p93" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>outlier</strong> &#8211; an extreme (unusual) score that falls far away from the rest of the scores in a set of data.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p94" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong><em>p</em> value</strong> &#8211; the probability of Type I error; the same as alpha level or significance level.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_G-4" block_type="page_start">G-4</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p95" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>paired samples</strong> &#8211; case selection for one sample is influenced by, depends on, the cases selected for another sample.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p96" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>paired-samples <em>t</em> test</strong> &#8211; hypothesis test used to compare the means of two dependent samples; also known as dependent-samples <em>t</em> test, correlated-samples <em>t</em> test, related-samples <em>t</em> test, matched-pairs <em>t</em> test, within-subjects <em>t</em> test, or repeated-measures <em>t</em> test.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p97" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>parameter</strong> &#8211; a value that summarizes a population.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p98" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>parametric test</strong> &#8211; a statistical test for use with interval- or ratio-level outcome variables, and for which assumptions about the shape of the population must be met.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p99" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>partial correlation</strong> &#8722; a correlation between two variables from which the influence of a third variable has been mathematically removed.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p100" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>Pearson correlation coefficient</strong> &#8722; a statistical test that measures the degree of linear relationship between two interval/ratio-level variables.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p101" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>percentile rank</strong> &#8211; percentage of cases with scores at or below a given level in a frequency distribution.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p102" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>perfect relationship</strong> &#8722; a relationship between two variables in which the value of one can be exactly predicted from the other.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p103" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>point estimate</strong> &#8211; an estimate of a population value that is a single value.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p104" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>pooled variance</strong> &#8211; the average variance for two samples.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p105" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>population</strong> &#8211; the larger group of cases a researcher is interested in studying.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p106" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>positive relationship</strong> &#8722; a relationship in which high scores on <em>X</em> are associated with high scores on <em>Y;</em> also called direct relationship.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p107" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>positive skew</strong> &#8211; an asymmetrical frequency distribution in which the tail extends to the right, in the direction of higher scores.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p108" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>post-hoc test</strong> &#8211; a follow-up test to a statistically significant ANOVA, engineered to find out which pairs of means differ while keeping the overall alpha level at the chosen level.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p109" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>power</strong> &#8211; the probability of rejecting the null hypothesis when the null hypothesis should be rejected.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p110" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>practical significance (or clinical significance)</strong> &#8211; the size of the effect is large enough to say the explanatory variable has a meaningful impact on the outcome variable (or the clinical outcome).</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p111" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>prediction interval</strong> &#8722; a range around <em>Y&#8242;</em> within which there is some certainty that a case&#8217;s real value of <em>Y</em> falls.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p112" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>predictor variable</strong> &#8722; the variable in a relationship test, <em>X</em>, that is used to predict the other variable, <em>Y;</em> the explanatory variable in a correlation design.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p113" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>pre-post design</strong> &#8211; participants are measured on the dependent variable before and after an intervention or manipulation.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p114" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>probability</strong> &#8211; how likely an outcome is; the number of ways a specific outcome can occur, divided by the total number of possible outcomes.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p115" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>quasi-experimental design</strong> &#8211; a scientific study in which cases are classified into naturally occurring groups and then compared on a dependent variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p116" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong><em>r</em><sup>2</sup></strong> &#8722; an effect size that reveals the percentage of variability in one variable that is accounted for by the other variable; formally called coefficient of determination.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p117" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>random assignment</strong> &#8211; every case has an equal chance of being assigned to any group in an experiment; random assignment is the hallmark of an experiment.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p118" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>random sample</strong> &#8211; a sampling strategy in which each case in the population has an equal chance of being selected.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p119" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>range</strong> &#8211; a measure of variability for interval- or ratio-level data; the distance from the lowest score to the highest score.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p120" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>rare zone</strong> &#8211; the section of the sampling distribution of a test statistic in which it is unlikely an observed outcome will fall if the null hypothesis is true; typically, 5&#37; of the sampling distribution.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p121" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>ratio-level numbers</strong> &#8211; numbers that have all the attributes of interval-level numbers, plus a real zero point; numbers that provide information about same/different, more/less, how much of an attribute is possessed, and that can be used to calculate a proportion.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p122" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>real limits</strong> &#8211; what are really the upper and lower bounds of a single continuous number or of an interval in a grouped frequency distribution.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p123" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>regression line</strong> &#8211; the best-fitting straight line for predicting <em>Y</em> from <em>X</em>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p124" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>relationship tests</strong> &#8211; statistical tests that determine if two variables in a group of cases covary.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p125" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>repeated-measures ANOVA</strong> &#8211; a statistical test used to compare two or more dependent samples on an interval- or ratio-level&#8211;dependent variable; also called within-subjects ANOVA, dependent-samples ANOVA, or related-samples ANOVA.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_G-5" block_type="page_start">G-5</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p126" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>repeated-measures design (or longitudinal research)</strong> &#8211; a study in which the same participants are measured at two or more points in time.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p127" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>replicate</strong> &#8211; to repeat a study, usually introducing some change in procedure to make it better.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p128" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>representative</strong> &#8211; the attributes of the population are present in the sample in approximately the same proportion as in the population.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p129" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>residual</strong> &#8211; the difference between an actual score and a predicted score; the size of the error in prediction.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p130" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>robust assumption</strong> &#8211; an assumption for a statistical test that can be violated to some degree and it is still OK to proceed with the test.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p131" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>sample</strong> &#8211; a group of cases selected from a population.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p132" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>sampling distribution</strong> &#8211; a frequency distribution generated by taking repeated, random samples from a population and generating some value, like a mean, for each sample.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p133" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>sampling error</strong> &#8211; discrepancies, due to random factors, between a sample statistic and a population parameter.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p134" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>self-selection bias</strong> &#8211; a nonrepresentative sample that may occur when the subjects who agree to participate in a research study differ from those who choose not to participate.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p135" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>significance level</strong> &#8211; the probability of Type I error; the same as alpha level or <em>p</em> value.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p136" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>simple linear regression</strong> &#8211; prediction in which <em>Y&#8242;</em> is predicted from a single predictor variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p137" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>single-sample test</strong> &#8211; a statistical test used to compare the results in a sample to a known population value or a specified value.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p138" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>single-sample <em>t</em> test</strong> &#8211; a statistical test that compares a sample mean to a population mean when the population standard deviation is not known.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p139" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>skewness</strong> &#8211; the degree to which a set of scores is not symmetric but tails off in one direction or the other.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p140" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>slope</strong> &#8211; the tilt of the line; rise over run; how much up or down change in <em>Y</em> is predicted for each 1-unit change in <em>X</em>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p141" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>Spearman rank-order correlation coefficient</strong> &#8211; a nonparametric test that examines the relationship between two ordinal-level variables or one ordinal and an interval/ratio variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p142" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>standard deviation</strong> &#8211; a measure of variability for interval- or ratio-level data; the square root of the variance; a measure of the average distance that scores fall from the mean.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p143" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>standard error of the estimate</strong> &#8211; the standard deviation of the residual scores, a measure of error in regression.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p144" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>standard error of the mean</strong> &#8211; the standard deviation of a sampling distribution of the mean.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p145" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>standard error of the mean difference for difference scores</strong> &#8211; the standard deviation of the sampling distribution of difference scores, abbreviated <em>S<sub>M<sub>D</sub></sub></em>; used as the denominator in the paired-samples <em>t</em> test equation.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p146" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>standard score</strong> &#8211; raw score expressed in terms of how many standard deviations it falls away from the mean; also known as a <em>z</em> score.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p147" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>statistic</strong> &#8211; a value that summarizes data from a sample.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p148" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>statistical significance</strong> &#8211; the observed difference between sample means is large enough to conclude that it represents a difference between population means.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p149" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>statistically significant</strong> &#8211; when a researcher concludes that the observed sample results are different from the null-hypothesized population value.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p150" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>statistics</strong> &#8211; techniques used to summarize data in order to answer questions.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p151" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>stem-and-leaf display</strong> &#8211; a data summary technique that combines features of a table and a graph.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p152" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>sum of squares</strong> &#8211; squaring a set of scores and then adding together the squared scores; abbreviated <em>SS</em>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p153" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>sum of squares between (<em>SS</em><sub>Between</sub>)</strong> &#8211; a sum of the squared deviation scores representing the variability between groups.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p154" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>sum of squares total (<em>SS</em><sub>Total</sub>)</strong> &#8211; a sum of the squared deviation scores representing all the variability in the scores.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p155" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>sum of squares within (<em>SS</em><sub>Within</sub>)</strong> &#8211; a sum of the squared deviation scores representing the variability within groups.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p156" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>treatment effect</strong> &#8211; the impact of the explanatory variable on the dependent variable.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p157" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>two-samples <em>t</em> test</strong> &#8211; an inferential statistical test used to compare the mean of one sample to the mean of another sample.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p158" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>two-tailed hypothesis test</strong> &#8211; hypothesis that predicts the explanatory variable has an impact on the outcome variable, but doesn&#8217;t predict the direction of the impact.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p159" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>Type I error</strong> &#8211; the error that occurs when the null hypothesis is true but is rejected; <em>p</em>(Type I error) = &#945;.</p>
<p id="corty3e_page_G-6" block_type="page_start">G-6</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p160" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>Type II error</strong> &#8211; the error that occurs when one fails to reject the null hypothesis but should have rejected it; <em>p</em>(Type II error) = &#946;.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p161" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>underpowered</strong> &#8211; term for a study with a sample size too small for the study to have a reasonable chance to reject the null hypothesis given the size of the effect.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p162" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>ungrouped frequency distribution</strong> &#8211; a count of how often each individual value of a variable occurs in a set of data.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p163" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>variability</strong> &#8211; how much variety (spread or dispersion) there is in a set of scores.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p164" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>variables</strong> &#8211; characteristics measured by researchers.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p165" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>variance</strong> &#8211; a measure of variability for interval- or ratio-level data; the mean of the squared deviation scores.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p166" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong>way</strong> &#8211; term for an explanatory variable in ANOVA.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p167" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>within-group variability</strong> &#8211; variability within a sample of cases, all of which have received the same treatment.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p168" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>within-subjects</strong> &#8211; ANOVA terminology for dependent samples.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p169" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong>within-subjects design</strong> &#8211; the same participants are measured in two or more different situations or under two or more different conditions.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p170" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong><em>Y</em>-intercept</strong> &#8211; the spot where the regression line would pass through the <em>Y</em>-axis.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p171" block_type="bm-gl-def"><strong><em>Y</em> prime</strong> &#8211; the value of <em>Y</em> predicted from <em>X</em> by a regression equation; <em>Y&#8242;</em>.</p>
<p id="corty3e-gls1-p172" block_type="bm-gl-def-a"><strong><em>z</em> score</strong> &#8211; raw score expressed in terms of how many standard deviations it falls away from the mean; also known as a standard score.</p>
</section>
</chapter>
